<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The whole duty of man epitomiz'd for the benefit of the poor. With select prayers suited to every partition. By Edm. Stacy, a minister of the Church of England.</title>
            <title>Whole duty of man. Abridgments</title>
            <author>Allestree, Richard, 1619-1681.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 134 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 73 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75032</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A1193A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R223863</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99900055</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99900055</idno>
            <idno type="VID">135637</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A75032)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 135637)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2505:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The whole duty of man epitomiz'd for the benefit of the poor. With select prayers suited to every partition. By Edm. Stacy, a minister of the Church of England.</title>
                  <title>Whole duty of man. Abridgments</title>
                  <author>Allestree, Richard, 1619-1681.</author>
                  <author>Stacy, Edmund, b. 1657 or 8.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 134, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for John Lawrence at the Angel in the Poultrey,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>An abridgment by Edmund Stacy of Richard Allestree's "Whole duty of man".</note>
                  <note>Published anonymously in 1658 with title:  "The practice of Christian graces, or, The whole duty of man" and variously attributed to Lady Dorothy Pakington, Archbishop Sterne, Bishop John Fell, and others, although now generally attributed to Richard Allestree--DNB.</note>
                  <note>With a final advertisement leaf.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Devotional exercises --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:135637:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:135637:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Whole Duty OF MAN Epitomiz'd FOR THE Benefit of the POOR. With Select Prayers ſuited to every <hi>Partition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y <hi>Edm. Stacy.</hi> a Miniſter of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ear God, and keep his Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; for this is the</hi> Whole Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Man,</p>
               <bibl> 
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12. 13.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>inted for <hi>John Lawrence</hi> at the <hi>Angel</hi> in the <hi>Poultrey,</hi> 1700.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:135637:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:135637:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the Right Honourable Sir</hi> Richard Levit, <hi>Lord Mayor Elect; And the Honourable</hi> Charles Duncomb, <hi>and</hi> Jeffery Jefferies <hi>Eſquires, She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffs of the City of</hi> London, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>IF there be any thing that can excuſe my Preſumption in putting Three ſuch great Names to this little Book, it muſt be the Sincerity of my Intention for the Intereſt of Religion.</p>
            <p>For the Doctrines it contains, I need ſay no more, than that they are faithfully Collected from that incomparable Author the <hi>Whole Duty of Man,</hi> a Book (to ſpeak in <hi>Dr. Hammond</hi>'s Words) that has
<pb facs="tcp:135637:3"/> all the Advantages, which (with Gods Bleſſing) can render it fit for the Salvation of Mankind.</p>
            <p>My Deſign in drawing it into this little Volume, I have already men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in the <hi>Title,</hi> viz. <hi>For the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of the Poor,</hi> and who ſo fit to recommend it to them, as thoſe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Perſons to whom the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this great City is entruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; your Names, your Characters, and your Authority together, muſt needs ſtamp a Repute upon it; and render it acceptable even to this ſin ful Age.</p>
            <p>I am ſenſible, there's neither of you can be any Friend to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Vanity of Complement; and therefore to beſpeak your Accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of theſe few Sheets; I ſhall Addreſs my Self to your gracious God, that under the ſhadow of your Protection, he would bleſs this Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomy to the Converſion of many Souls.</p>
            <p>Alas! we live in a World where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Vertue has almoſt loſt her Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative, Religion has few true
<pb facs="tcp:135637:3"/> Friends and will have fewer ſtill, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ill Men can be perſuaded to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er the Neceſſity and Advantage of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t; and how far this little Book <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay contribute towards that End is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tterly out of my Power to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ine.</p>
            <p>I know I have put it into good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ands, and ſo I humbly leave it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ith you, with this Aſſurance, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hatever you do in the behalf of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iety and Charity, will be doubly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ac'd to your Account in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ords of Eternity, and entitle you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Rewards as large as your Merits, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d as laſting as your Souls.</p>
            <p>And now there remains no more, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t to beſeech you to accept this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tle Book, and Pardon the unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y Author, who amongſt many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ers that Congratulate your Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſion to your reſpective Stations, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> one of the firſt that has thus ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r'd to do it in Publick.</p>
            <p>Your high Qualifications have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>awn after you many Hearts, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>any ardent Wiſhes, and Mine in
<pb facs="tcp:135637:4"/> a more Particular manner than th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> reſt, who am with the utmoſt D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and Regard, may it plea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> your Honours,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt obedient Servant, E. Stac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:135637:4"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R Inimitable Author has pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd the Care of our Souls as the grand Proparatory to the <hi>Whole Duty of Man,</hi> and indeed I cannot better recommend the <hi>Epitomy</hi> of his Book, then by telling you in his Words, that the careleſneſs of our Souls is the Root of all the Sin we commit; ſo that unleſs we would be perſwaded to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Condition of our Souls, all Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures of Religion muſt be utterly loſt upon us.</p>
            <p>The Deſign of this little Book will admit of but a very ſhort Preface, and therefore I ſhall only tell the Reader, that his Soul being infinitely the moſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>valuable of any thing that he has be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, has the greateſt Title to his <q>Care both in Point of Reaſon and Juſtice.</q>
            </p>
            <p>This is what we find confirm'd in the Accounts of all Wiſe Men, who ſtill value every thing more or leſs, as it
<pb facs="tcp:135637:5"/> imports to their Intereſt or Happineſs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Our Souls therefore being our chiefeſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Good, it concerns us very nearly t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> conſult their Preſervation, and how that's to be done, is the Deſign of the following Sheets.</p>
            <p>I hope it will not be expected, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſhould ſay any thing in Apology for this undertaking. If the thing be done a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it ought to be, it muſt needs be of ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral good; the Reader indeed woul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> do well to obſerve, that though my Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> has generally compell'd m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to uſe my own Words, yet the Meaning and Method of the Author are all along carefully preſerv'd.</p>
            <p>For the <hi>Whole Duty of Man</hi> it ſelf 'tis indeed a moſt compleat Syſtem o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Religion, and therefore highly fit to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> often read over at large by all, whoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Time and Circumſtances will allow it; This Epitomy is only deſign'd t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſupply thoſe Deficiencies, and for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Aſſiſtance of bad Memories; in brief 'tis intended chiefly <hi>for the Benefit of the Poor,</hi> and to them I refer it <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:135637:5"/>
            <head>THE Whole Duty OF MAN Epitomiz'd, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>PARTITION I.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>the Duty of Man by the Light of Nature, and Scripture: His Duty to God, Himſelf, and his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour. His Duty to God; of Faith, the Promiſes, of Hope, of Love, of Fear, of Truſt.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THE Incarnation of our Bleſſed Lord, is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt a ſufficient warrant for the Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>n of our Souls, if we perform the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:135637:6"/> Conditions annext to it; which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in general to uſe our honeſt endea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to obey the whole Will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> God, according as we have it co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey'd to us, by the Light of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and the Light of the Hol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Scriptures.</p>
               <p>The Light of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in the firſt pla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <note place="margin">Of the Light of Nature.</note> is a Light which Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> has ſtampt upon o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> very Souls, by the guidance <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> which, without the help of Scri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture mere Natural Conſcience wou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> direct us in the performance <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſeveral Duties. Such as are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Worſhip a God, to be Juſt one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> another, and to Honour our P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, and the like.</p>
               <p>The Light of Scri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures is a far mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <note place="margin">Of the Light of Scripture.</note> Divine Light, whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in God hath laid b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us both his Commands, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Precepts, to be the general Rul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and Grounds of our Duty.</p>
               <p>The general Rules of the Du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of every Chriſtian are brie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:135637:6"/> comprehended under theſe three Heads; <note place="margin">The three great Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Mans Duty.</note> our Duty to God, our Selves, and our Neighbours, and thoſe three I intend for the Subject of the following Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe.</p>
               <p>The Foundation of our Duty to God, is <note place="margin">Duty to God</note> grounded chiefly up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our acknowledging him to be God, and then admitting of no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>And firſt by ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging <note place="margin">Acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him to be God.</note> him to be a God, we are to believe him to be an Infinite Glorious Being, without either beginning or end, both Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, God bleſſed for ever.</p>
               <p>We are likewiſe to <note place="margin">To believe him in his Attributes.</note> believe him in his Attributes; to be a God of Mercy, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and Power, that he ſees and knows all things, and diſpoſes eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:135637:7"/> Event, according to his Will, and that he can never ceaſe to be other than perfectly Good, Merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and Juſt.</p>
               <p>The believing him to be our God ſignifies yet more, it means by Faith we ſhould believe the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures to be his Word, and that all that he ſpeaks to us by them, are moſt true; that all that he affirms is Indubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, that his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands <note place="margin">Of Faith, of God's Affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations, Commands, Threatnings, and Promiſes</note> are Juſt, and Equal, his Threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings and Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments certain and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avoidable, and that all his Promiſes are <hi>Yea</hi> and <hi>Amen,</hi> and will moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly be made good to all thoſe that faithfully depend upon him.</p>
               <p>This is the ſumm of our Faith, or Belief of thoſe things God has been pleaſed to reveal to us in the Holy Scriptures.</p>
               <p>The next Duty to God is Hope, which is a comfortable Expectation of his Promiſes, and ſhould be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:135637:7"/> preſerv'd from the dangerous ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream <note place="margin">Of Hope, Preſumption, and Deſpair.</note> of Preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or Deſpair; We ſhould neither de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend to much, nor too little upon his. Mercies, but rely upon his Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and Integrity for our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards and Puniſhments.</p>
               <p>A Third Duty we owe to God is Love, <note place="margin">Of Love and the Motives, <hi>i. e.</hi> Gods Goodneſs, Excellence, and his kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to Men.</note> a Duty which with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt he has the the greateſt right to, both upon the account of his Goodneſs and Compaſſion to us, his Innate Excellence, and his particular Kindneſs to all Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind.</p>
               <p>God is moſt Good, Juſt and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent, he is perfectly Holy, Kind, and Compaſſionate, and cannot be charg'd with any Impurity, or the leaſt mixture of any thing that is evil; his Goodneſs and Kindneſs are Immence and Infinite, and have been ſo abundantly demonſtrated
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:135637:8"/> both to our Bodies and Souls, that we cannot refuſe him our Love without the greateſt Injuſtice.</p>
               <p>The Scripture abound with Holy Invitations, endearing Promiſes and affectionate Offers, by which he endeavours, as it were, to woo us into good Lives, and to entreat us to accept of Happineſs here and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Happineſs hereafter.</p>
               <p>The two great To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens of our true <note place="margin">The Fruits of Love, a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to pleaſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and enjoy him.</note> Love to God are Firſt, An earneſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to pleaſe him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and Secondly, To enjoy him. This is the common Indication of true Love in all ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Caſes; and above all othe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> things doth beſt approve us to thoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> we have a real value for.</p>
               <p>The reality of ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Affections to Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <note place="margin">Of pleaſing God.</note> are beſt declar'd, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a ſteady Conformit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to the Divine Will, a readineſs t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> obey his Commandments, and a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> awful regard to his Precepts; the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:135637:8"/> are indeed Arguments of our real Love, and Affection, and the only way we can make uſe of, either to pleaſe him, or to ſhew the ſinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of our Hearts.</p>
               <p>Next to pleaſing <note place="margin">Of enjoying him.</note> God, a deſire to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy him is conſiſtent with our Love; if we love God in earneſt we ſhall covet to be always in his Company, converſing with him in Prayers and Meditations, hearing his Word and receiving his Sacraments, which is the only means of enjoying God in this World.</p>
               <p>Our enjoyment of God in the next is far more permanent and compleat; there we ſhall be conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually with him in eternal fruition of Joy and Happineſs, in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of which all our advantages in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>his Life are but empty Baubles and Trifles.</p>
               <p>A Fourth Duty to <note place="margin">Fear.</note> God is Fear, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>riſes from the conſideration of his Power and Juſtice; and thoſe in Conjunction, do both enable, and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:135637:9"/> oblige him to puniſh the Wicked an awful regard and belief of which is the only means that can reſtr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> us from offending him.</p>
               <p>God is the chiefeſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Object of Fear, and <note place="margin">We ought not to fear Man more than God.</note> therefore we ough<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not to fear Man mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> than God. <hi>I will no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> fear,</hi> ſays the Pſal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt, <hi>what Man can do unto me.</hi> Me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> have no Power to do us hurt unleſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> by God's Permiſſion, and then the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Malice can reach no further neithe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> than our Goods, Names, Liberties or our Lives; the Deſtruction o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Soul and Body together is Gods Pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative only.</p>
               <p>'Tis God alone that knows a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> our ſecret Thoughts and Tranſact<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, all our Sins though committe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with never ſo much Privacy, lie al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways open before him, and he'll b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſure to find us out, and puniſh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> unleſs we repent, which indeed i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the greateſt Argument that can b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to awaken our Fears and engage ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Apprehenſions.</p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:135637:9"/>
               <p>A Fifth Duty to God is Truſt, that is, <note place="margin">Truſt.</note> a depending and reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon him in all our Dangers. Wants and Extremities, whether Spiritual or Temporal.</p>
               <p>In our Spiritual Dangers, we are to <note place="margin">Spiritual Dangers.</note> throw our ſelves up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on God's Aſſiſtance, and to implore him to ſtrengthen us with the Grace of his Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that we may be able to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, or at leaſt to remove the Temptation.</p>
               <p>In our Temporal <note place="margin">Temporal Dangers.</note> Dangers we are to reſt and depend up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, to commit our ſelves to the ſhadow of his Wings, under the Royal Prophets Aſſurance, <hi>Pſalm <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>4. 22. That the Lord delivereth the Souls of the Saints, and all that put their truſt in him ſhall not be deſtitute.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In all our Dangers and Diſtreſſes, with Prayers and Tears we are to implore his aid, and not attempt to deliver our ſelves by any wicked
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:135637:10"/> Act; we muſt never uſe ſinful means, not <note place="margin">We muſt not ſeek to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver our ſelves by Sin.</note> even the Preſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our Lives and Liberties can make any the leaſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence for the doing an unjuſt thing; Chriſt himſelf has told us, that <hi>if we gain the whole World and looſe our own Souls,</hi> we are great looſers by the Bargain; if therefore things ſhould ever come to that unhappy Iſſue, that we muſt part with our Eſtates, perhaps our Lives, or elſe commit Sin, we ſhould then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that that's the proper ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to fight under the Banner of the great Captain of our Salvation, the <hi>Crucify'd JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In our ſpiritual Neceſſities we are to <note place="margin">Spiritual wants.</note> fly to God with Tears in our Eyes and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke his Aſſiſtance, we are to pour out our Souls before him, and then we may depend upon it, that as he has commanded us nothing that he has not given us Power to perform,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:135637:10"/> ſo he will ſuffer us to want nothing that we aſk of him with a holy and devout Integrity of mind.</p>
               <p>We are likewiſe to rely upon him in all <note place="margin">Temporal wants.</note> our Temporal and Bodily Wants; he has oblig'd himſelf to take care of all his faithful Servants, his Eye is upon them that fear him, and them that hope in his Mercy, to deliver their Souls from Death, and to feed them in the time of Famine.</p>
               <p>If we do our Duty honeſtly and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly <note place="margin">The Benefits of truſting in God.</note> in our ſeveral Places and Callings, then as the Apoſtle adviſeth we may caſt all our Care upon God who careth for us, and he who is ſubject to no ſort of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit or Impoveriſhment, that beſt knows our wants, and is beſt able to ſupply 'em, will be ſure in the proper ſeaſon, to relieve us againſt all Dangers and Neceſſities whether Spiritual or Temporal.</p>
               <p>I conclude this with the words of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:135637:11"/> the Apoſtle, <hi>Phil. 4. 6. Be careful in nothing, but in every thing by Prayer and Supplication, with thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving, let your Requeſt be made known to God.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>PARTITION II.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of Humility, of Submiſſion to God's Will, in reſpect of Obedience, of Patience in all ſorts of Sufferings and of Honour due to God in ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ways, in his Houſe, Poſſeſſions his Day, Word, Sacraments.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>A Sixth Duty to <note place="margin">Humility.</note> God is Humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which from an humble ſence of our own Meanneſs and his Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency ſhould work in us a twofold Submiſſion, the firſt to his Will, the ſecond to his Wiſdom.</p>
               <p>A Submiſſion to the Will of God con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts <note place="margin">Submiſſion to God's Will, with reſpect to Obedience.</note> chiefly in our O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience or Patience, in the firſt by urging
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:135637:11"/> us to a ready Complaiſance to his Commands, by melting down our ſtubborn haughty Minds, without which we can never come to know, worſhip, or obey him, with that profound Diſtance and Submiſſion which the greatneſs of his Majeſty, and the importance of his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands require.</p>
               <p>To promote our O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, <note place="margin">The great diſtance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween God and Man.</note> we ſhould often reflect upon that vaſt diſtance that is between God and our Selves, that we are but pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Duſt and Aſhes, wretched Creatures but of a few Hours, and that he's without Beginning or End, Immortal and Eternal.</p>
               <p>That our beſt Works and Perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances <note place="margin">The unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſs of our beſt Works.</note> are utterly unworthy of him, or at leaſt unworthy of our own Commendation, the beſt we can do when we come to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare it with the Perfection and Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of Almighty God, as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:135637:12"/> expreſſes it, <hi>Is but as filthy Rags,</hi> and therefore we ought by no means to boaſt of our own Works or to attribute any of them to our ſelves, but to give God the Glory and preheminence in all our Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
               <p>The Second kind of Submiſſion to Gods <note place="margin">Submiſſion with reſpect of Patience.</note> Will is Patience, which conſiſts in an humble acquieſcence to all the Afflictions which HE is pleas'd to lay upon us. This will make us ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie under all his Diſpenſations, and entitle us to a kind of Repoſe even in the midſt of our Troubles, and is indeed the pure effect of that Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility that does ſo highly recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend us to Almighty God.</p>
               <p>A patient Submiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to the Will o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <note place="margin">Thankfulneſs for Gods cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.</note> God will give us <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> right notion of our Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions rather than encline us to murmurs and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints, will convince us, that God chaſtizes us out of Friendſhip, and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:135637:12"/> ſo conſequently that we are oblig'd to thank him for his Correction, as indeed we are upon many extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Accounts, but eſpecially as they are Marks of his Care and Love.</p>
               <p>Our quiet, and <note place="margin">Fruitfulneſs under Affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions.</note> thankfulneſs under Afflictions is not all neither, the Fruit of 'em ſhould be Repentance, that's God's chief Deſign in laying them upon us; that they ſhould force us to call our ſelves to an account, and enquire diligently what it is that has engag'd him to deal with us in ſo rough a method.</p>
               <p>In all our Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings <note place="margin">In all ſorts of Sufferings.</note> and Afflictions we ought to look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on God's permiſſive Power as the Principle Agent, and with Holy <hi>Job</hi>'s Patience, let them be deriv'd to us either from God or Man; and in his Words, bleſs the Name of the Lord for giving us warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               <p>Secondly, I told you that Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:135637:13"/> contain'd likewiſe a Submiſſion to God's <note place="margin">Submiſſion to Gods Wiſdom</note> Wiſdom, as well as his Will; God being infinitely Wiſe and Juſt, we are to ſubmit to him in all his Commands and Diſpenſations.</p>
               <p>We are to ſubmit to him in his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, <note place="margin">In his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands.</note> by making our Underſtanding <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>end to his Will and Word, how oppoſite ſoever it may be to our own carnal Reaſon or Humours, for when we conſider that his Wiſdom is Infinite and cannot Err, we own an Obligation to believe and obey every thing he ſpeaks or commands.</p>
               <p>We are likewiſe to ſubmit to the Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom <note place="margin">In his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſals.</note> of God in all his Dealings and Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations, and tho many Events hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen contrary to the ordinary Courſe of things, and are utterly above the reach of our narrow Capacities to comprehend, yet being all cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen and determin'd by the unerring
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:135637:13"/> Wiſdom of God, we ought to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to them, with the greateſt Satisfaction and Humility.</p>
               <p>The next Duty to God is Honour, which <note place="margin">Honour.</note> conſiſts in the paying him ſuch a reſpect and Reverence as belongs to the greatneſs of his Majeſty, and this may be either in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly in our Hearts, or outward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in our publick Actions, and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour towards him.</p>
               <p>Beſides, the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, there are parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular <note place="margin">Several ways of honouring God, in his Houſe and Poſſeſſions.</note> Ways of honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring God, as Firſt, By approaching his Houſe, the Church with Reverence, and behaving our ſelves there with De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion and Attention; Secondly, In his Poſſeſſions by paying our Tithes and Juſt, Dues which God has appointed for the maintenance of his Miniſters.</p>
               <p>The Sin of Sacriledge and defrau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Miniſtry, is a very great and crying Sin; 'tis the downright
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:135637:14"/> robbing of God, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> indeed his Vengean<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <note place="margin">The great ſin of Sacrilege and the Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of it.</note> is in nothing mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> diſcernable then in h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Puniſhment of it; u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which account w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſhould have a ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſtrict Care never to medle with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing ſet a part for God.</p>
               <p>The Third Thin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> whereby we are t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <note place="margin">The Lords Day and Feaſts of the Church to be kept Holy.</note> expreſs our reverenc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to God, is by keepin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Holy the particula<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Times ſet a part fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his Service, ſuch a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> are the Sunday's, or Lords-days and other ſolemn Feſtivals appoint<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Church; this he ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſtrictly requir'd of us, and herei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> we muſt not diſappoint him upo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> any pretence.</p>
               <p>Days of Faſting an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Humiliation are like wiſe <note place="margin">The Faſts.</note> to be ſolemnl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> obſerv'd, that according to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of the Church, we may mee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> together, and humble our ſelve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:135637:14"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eeply before God, and with Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and Tears bewail our own and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Sins of the Nation.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, We are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o expreſs our Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour <note place="margin">God's word the Holy Scriptures.</note> to God, by pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng an awful Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ence and reſpect to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is Word, by frequent reading the Holy Scriptures, and by collecting <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he meaſures of a good Life from thoſe lively Oracles; by attending upon the Duties of Religion, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y being preſent as often as we may at the publick Catechizings and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons.</p>
               <p>Catechizing in the <note place="margin">Of Catechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing.</note> firſt Place is the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation upon which the whole Chriſtian Practice muſt be built, 'tis therefore the Duty of every Parent to have his Children early inſtructed in the Church Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſm, and for this end they are to call in the help of their reſpective Miniſters; and for thoſe that have been ſo unhappy to want theſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions in their Youth, it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:135637:15"/>
'em as nearly as their Sou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to have their minds Principl'd wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the Conditions of their Salvati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> as ſoon as they can, which neith<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the Conſideration of their Age, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> any other pretence ſhould perſwa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> them to defer for one Moment.</p>
               <p>After they are i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed in the Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples <note place="margin">Of Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</note> of their Relig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, they ought th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> to apply themſelves to the heari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of Sermons, which they ought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> attend too, not out of Cuſtome Formality, but for the true ends f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> which they were firſt intende<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> The Doctrines are to be lockt up our Hearts, that we may have 'e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> in a readineſs to combate all o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Luſt and Follies, and to beat off a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> our Temptations; this is the gre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> end of Preaching, and unleſs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> make this uſe of it, it ſignifies litt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> towards the Salvation of our Souls.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, We are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Honour God in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſtrict <note place="margin">Of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments.</note> Reverence <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the two Sacraments
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:135637:15"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Baptiſm, and the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>r; the firſt we are to reſpect a particular Covenant between <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>d and our ſelves, the firſt and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>lie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t Sign of our Salvation; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>e ſecond as a remembrance of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>riſt's Death, and the Priviledges <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>riv'd to us upon that account.</p>
               <p>The Sacrament of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>ptiſm being admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>tred <note place="margin">Of Baptiſm.</note> to us in our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ancy. It is not expected from to perform the Covenants which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> engage our ſelves to by our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>reties, but then this lays the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>eater Obligation upon us when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>e come to Years of Diſcretion, to double our Duty, that we may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>ake the beſt amends we can, for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>e defects of our Minority.</p>
               <p>To come to a true Knowledge of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>e Duties we Promiſe at our Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>m; the right way will be to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>er what our God fathers and God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> others Vow in our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>ames, and that we <note place="margin">The Vow of Baptiſm.</note> all find to be, <hi>to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>unce the Devil and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:135637:16"/> all his Works,</hi> by which is meant t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Worſhipping all falſe Gods, whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> is indeed the worſhipping the D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil; Secondly, <hi>The Pomps and Va<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the World,</hi> that is, all inor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate deſires of Riches and Gre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, all unlawful Sports and Ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in Meat or Apparel, and all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſinful things wherein t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> World is apt to deceive us; a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Thirdly, The ſinful Luſt of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Fleſh, by which is underſtood <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> inordinate Appetites, and all u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> clean and carnal Deſires, and t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> is the firſt part of our Covenant.</p>
               <p>The ſecond general Thing o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> God-fathers and God-mothers p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis'd for us in our Baptiſm; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> that we ſhould believe all the A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of the Chriſtian Faith, as th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> are ſumm'd up to us in the Ap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles Creed, and not barely belie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> them neither, but to have all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Principles ſo deeply impreſs'd a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> engraven in our Minds, that fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> thence we may be able to draw ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient Motives to the Practice Vertue and Piety.</p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:135637:16"/>
               <p>The laſt part of our Vow is, that we ſhould keep Gods Holy Will and Commandments, and walk in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ame all the Days of our Lives; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat is, that according to the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ections of Gods word, we ſhould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>alk all our Days in the Paths of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rue Religion, Honeſty and Sobri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ty.</p>
               <p>This being in ſhort <note place="margin">The ſtrict ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligations of this Vow of Baptiſm.</note> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Subſtance of our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ow, the next thing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Obligations we all under to perform <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t, and herein I need only tell you, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tis a Vow of the moſt ſolemn and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inding Nature, and that you cannot <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reak it without being not only un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſt, but forſworn; beſides, 'tis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ur Intereſt to keep it upon many Accounts, but eſpecially upon the Account of the great Priviledges it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>titles us to, from the Promiſes of God convey'd to us in that Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ent.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:135637:17"/>
               <head>PARTITION III.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of the Sacrament of the Lords Supp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> of Preparation before, as Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, of Repentance, Faith, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Obedience, of Duties to be done <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the Receiving, and afterward<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>THE Reverenc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <note place="margin">The Lords Supper.</note> due to the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the Lord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Supper is the next thing, which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to my firſt Diviſion, I ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> conſider by laying down what is t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> be done before, at, and after th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Receiving.</p>
               <p>The firſt thing t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> be done before th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <note place="margin">Things to be done before Receiving. The firſt is Examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> Sacrament is Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, which is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſtrict enquiry into th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſtate of our Souls and the Condition o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> our Lives, and thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> in the Judgment of St. <hi>Paul</hi> is ſo
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:135637:17"/> eſſentially neceſſary, that we ought not to preſume to make any ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches towards the Holy Table without it.</p>
               <p>For the perfecting your Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, you are to conſider the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of your Covenant, which is a renewal of your Baptiſmal Vow, and ſince that is the chief end, three things follow in Courſe; Firſt, That we be well Inſtructed in the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant it ſelf. Secondly, What have been our Breaches? And Thirdly, Then that we reſolve upon a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Performance for the Future, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd theſe Three are to be the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eral Grounds of our Examination.</p>
               <p>And Firſt, You'll find that, this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s a Covenant made by God with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is Son Chriſt Jeſus for the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>emption of all Mankind, and that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Conditions on our ſide, are an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ire Obedience to all his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ands, and the ſtate of our Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>dge in this, is the firſt part of our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xamination.</p>
               <p>The next is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erning <note place="margin">Sins.</note> our Breaches
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:135637:18"/> of this Covenant, which we can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver know with that exactneſs as w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ought, without comparing them with the Law of God, which as i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is the trueſt rule and meaſure <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> our Duty; ſo 'tis the beſt means t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> lead us to the Knowledge and Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of our Sins.</p>
               <p>Our Sins alas! a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of many ſorts and d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> grees, <note place="margin">Several ſorts and degrees.</note> and require great deal both of o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Judgment and Deliberation to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire aright into their Cauſes, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Conſequences. It requires a grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> deal of Skill to heighten and aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate the Circumſtances of our Guil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to that degree, till we come at la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to a true Sence of the hainouſne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of them.</p>
               <p>The end of Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation is to bring <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to <note place="margin">Humiliation and Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> this, and to a rig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Knowledge of o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Sins, to humble us <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the ſight of God, and to melt o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Hearts into a deep Sorrow and Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition upon the Conſideration <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:135637:18"/> our Demerits and Injuſtice towards him; we are likewiſe to Pray for the Aſſiſtance of God's Spirit in the diſcovery of all our Sins, and for his Grace that we may throughly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ail and lament them.</p>
               <p>After we have wrought our ſelves, <note place="margin">Confeſſion and Faith.</note> by the aſſiſtance of our Examination to a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ixt hatred and averſion againſt all our Sins, then we are humbly to confeſs 'em to Almighty God, who by the precious Blood of his Son Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, we are faithfully to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, will be reconcil'd to us, and upon the account of our intire Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience will vouchſafe us the Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our Souls.</p>
               <p>And then, when <note place="margin">Reſolutions of Obedience.</note> we have thus exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min'd and prepar'd our ſelves with reſpect to our Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation and Contrition, our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion and Faith, the next thing is our Reſolution of Obedience, which muſt not be only in general, but with a particular regard to every
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:135637:19"/> individual Commandment of Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> deriv'd from a fixt and ſolid hatr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> againſt all manner of Sins.</p>
               <p>The means of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> new and intire Ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience <note place="margin">Of the means and of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of Sin.</note> muſt be o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> next Care, which w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> be beſt perfected <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> an impartial retr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> into our own Minds; there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> may diſcover the Springs and Fou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of our Sins, and what Tem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations we are expos'd to, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> be in a capacity to ſhun and avo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> them; and this muſt be done i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> mediately too, without any ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Delay or Pretence; for t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> it be done, and a Bill of Divorce g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to every Luſt, we are in no r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect fit to meet our Redeemer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Holy Table.</p>
               <p>Beſide this, we a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> to put our Souls in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <note place="margin">Of imbracing Vertue and quickning Graces.</note> the beſt poſture th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> we can, by imbracin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> all the Vertues of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> good Life, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> poſſeſſing them with all thoſe Gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:135637:19"/> that may render them accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in the Eyes of God, and this we may do effectually, by contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Promiſes and goodneſs of God, and by meditating upon the exemplary Life and Doctrine of our bleſſed Lord.</p>
               <p>His Life will put us <note place="margin">Charity and Devotion and the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of thoſe Graces.</note> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n mind of that Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and forgiving temper, which is ſo often, and ſolemnly requir'd of us, and ſo eſſentially neceſſary in our Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Preparations; 'tis Death for us to approach God's Feaſt of Love, with any manner of Ranchor or Malice; we are to bring no other Diſpoſitions thither, but what are dictated to us from a devout Mind. A fixt and ſettled Devotion, ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt and frequent Prayers, and a Soul diſentangled from the World, are our propereſt Companions for this Sacrament, and for theſe we are earneſtly to implore God's Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, without whoſe help in aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting us with the Graces afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:135637:20"/> we can never expect <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> compleat our Preparations.</p>
               <p>And for the better perfecting a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> this, we are to apply our ſelves <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> our ſpiritual Guide, to the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of our own Pariſh, who is th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> propereſt Perſon in this Caſe; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> him without any manner of reſerv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> we are to declare our Doubts an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Jealouſies, and to take his Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and Directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and herein <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſort <note place="margin">The uſeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Guide. We ſhould not be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſham'd to diſcover our ſelves.</note> of ſhame to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover ourſelves ough<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to deter or diſincou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage us; we ough<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to open our Caſe fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and Impartially that he may know perfectly how matter ſtand between God and our Soul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and then he will be able to give u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Advice how to cure both ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Doubts and our Sins the doubtful an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <note place="margin">As neceſſary to the Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent as the Doubtful.</note> the confident are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually oblig'd to this our own Judgment
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:135637:20"/> are not intirely to be relied upon, in a Concern where there is ſo much weight and difficulty, nor is the Advantage of a ſpiritual Guide to be rejected, when it can be of uſe in the Improvement of our Prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</p>
               <p>Theſe are the Duties before the Sacrament. The next thing is, what is to be done at the Time of Receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; <note place="margin">At the time of Receiving to meditate upon our un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthineſs and Chriſt's Sufferings.</note> and here, Firſt, Conſider thy own un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthineſs, and how unfit thy Sins and Frailties, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated breach of thy Vows, have render'd thee for ſuch a Holy Table; from hence, let thy Meditations lead thee to the Sufferings of Chriſt. When we ſee the Bread broken, and the Wine pour'd out, we ſhould reflect that his bleſſed Body was torn, and his Blood ſplit, and that it was our Sins that was the Cauſe of both.</p>
               <p>Conſider likewiſe that the Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of Chrſt were the only means
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:135637:21"/> to attone the wrath of God, and then <note place="margin">The Atonement wrought by them; thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for them, the Love of Chriſt in them.</note> conſider what un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expreſſible thanks are due to him for preſerving thy Sou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that muſt have periſh'd eternally without his help; this great Love of Chriſt for us, ſhould ſtir up in us a love for him, and engage us immediately to take up ſolemn Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions to Sin no more, and that we may indeed perform theſe Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions, we ought earneſtly to beg of this crucified Saviour, that he will by the Power of his Death, mortifie and kill all our Corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
               <p>Juſt as we are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to receive the <note place="margin">The Benefits of the new Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant ſeal'd in the Sacrament.</note> Conſecrated Bread and Wine, we ſhould remember that then God is entring into a New Covenant with us, that he's now giving us freſh Aſſurances of the Pardon of our Sins, if we per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:135637:21"/> our part of the Condition; as ſoon as we have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd, we ought to <note place="margin">
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, give thanks, and Pray.</note> offer him our devou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Praiſes for that great Mercy, and ſhould be ſure never to forget to ſend up our Prayers to him, not more for our ſelves than for the good Eſtate of the Church, and for the Converſion of all Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind.</p>
               <p>After the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <note place="margin">After the Sacrament, private pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and Thankſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings.</note> is over, then we ought as ſoon as Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, to retire our ſelves, and to repeat again our Prayers and Praiſes, and to renew our Promiſes, and to beg the Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of God's Grace to enable us to make 'em good, and to purſue our preſent Purpoſes to the end of our Lives.</p>
               <p>The Day we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive <note place="margin">Not preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to fall to worldly Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs.</note> the Sacrament ſhould be kept void of all worldly Cares
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:135637:22"/> and Buſineſs; we ſhould ſpend that Day eſpecially in Prayers and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations; and indeed no Day ſhould paſs, but we ſhould call to mind the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes <note place="margin">To keep our Reſolutions, and the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them.</note> we make to God at the Sacrament, and conſider ſeriouſly the danger we expoſe ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſelves to in breaking them.</p>
               <p>In breaking ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Vows at the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <note place="margin">Making God and our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience our E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy.</note> we make God our Enemy, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage him to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw from us all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Kindneſs and Compaſſion; nay, we raiſe an Enemy within ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> own Boſom; our Conſcience muſt needs fly in our Face, and upbraid us with the breach of ſuch ſolemn Vows and Covenants.</p>
               <p>Gods Mercies in pardoning us heretofore ſhould not give us the leaſt encouragement to provoke him again; to preſume upon this is a very high abuſe of his goodneſs;
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:135637:22"/> The obligation of our Sacramental Vows are <note place="margin">God's form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er pardons n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the vow perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, yet often to be renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</note> perpetual, and can never be violated without the breach of our Oaths; 'tis per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual, 'tis true, and yet 'tis to be renew'd often, We are to do it as often as we have opportunity in remembrance that Chriſt died for us. And thus I have ſhew'd you the Reverence we are to pay to God in his Sacrament.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <head>PARTITION IV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Honour due to God's Name; Sin's a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, Blaſphemy, Swearing, of Aſſertory, Promiſſory, unlawful Oaths, of Perjury, vain Oaths, and the Sin of them.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THE laſt thing <note place="margin">Honour due to God's Name.</note> wherein we are to expreſs a Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to God is in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouring
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:135637:23"/> his Name, and what this is, will be beſt underſtood by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering what are the Things by which it is chiefly diſhonoured.</p>
               <p>The firſt Sin againſt the Honour of God's <note place="margin">Sins againſt it Blaſphemy and Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</note> Name is Blaſphemy, the higheſt Degree of which is Curſing him either by our Words or in our Thoughts, and next to that, Swearing either by falſe Oaths or elſe by raſh and light ones.</p>
               <p>A falſe Oath may be of two kinds; as <note place="margin">Aſſertory Oaths and Promiſſory.</note> Firſt, That by which I affirm ſome thing; or, Secondly, That by which I Promiſe; the one we call an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Aſſertory, and the other a Promiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſory Oath, and are both a very great diſhonour to God's Name, when they are not taken with Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity and Truth, and perform'd with reality.</p>
               <p>An Oath is the ſtrongeſt Tie that can <note place="margin">
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlawful Oaths.</note> be between Man and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:135637:23"/> Man, but yet if it be unlawful in it ſelf and contradictory, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>practicable in the Nature of it, in ſuch a Caſe, though the breach e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of ſuch an Oath be a very great Sin, yet 'tis better to repent hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily of our Folly and Wickedneſs in making ſuch a ſinful and inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate Oath, then to attempt with greater Sin and Danger in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of it.</p>
               <p>There is nothing <note place="margin">God greatly diſhonoured by Perjury, and the Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments of it.</note> by which the Name of God is more diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured then by Perju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, 'tis the higheſt affront can be offer'd to him, and indeed we find him reſenting nothing with more juſt ſeverity, then this kind of Violation of his Honour, <hi>He will not hold him guiltleſs,</hi> he has de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clar'd <hi>that taketh his Name in vain,</hi> which is ſo dreadful a menace, that methinks it ſhould engage every one that has any value for his Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, to keep them moſt ſtrictly from this Sin.</p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:135637:24"/>
               <p>All vain and light Oaths, ſuch as are ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <note place="margin">Vain Oaths and the Sin of them.</note> common in our Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes, are likewiſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> very high offence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Majeſty of the Name <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> God. Our Saviour has forbidde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> us to ſwear, even by mere Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, to ſhew us, I preſume the Reverence we ought to have fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Name of their Creator; and ſure whatever this prophane Ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> may think of it, there is nothing does more argue a Contempt o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> God, then to hear his Name inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mix'd in every Period of looſe Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe. and violated every Momen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with horrid and impertinent Oaths.</p>
               <p>This ſort of vain and raſh Swearin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <note place="margin">They lead to Perjury, and are liable to no Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> leads directly to Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury, we grow at la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſo Familiar with th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Name of God, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> at length we can uſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it upon any occaſion, without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering whether we ſware true <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> falſe to things doubtful or certain
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:135637:24"/> beſide this too there is no manner of Temptation for this ſort of leud Swearing, there is no kind of Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure or Profit in it, nor any thing elſe to recommend it, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequenely 'tis a baſe Sin, which we wilfully commit without any manner of excuſe or Pretence.</p>
               <p>'Tis a dangerous Vice, and therefore <note place="margin">The Neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of abſtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from them; the means; the Sence of the Guilt and Danger.</note> every Man that va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lues the Salvation of his Soul, ought to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce it with the greateſt Caution and Concern; the means are always ready be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, <hi>viz.</hi> the Sence of the Guilt and Danger of it, when he conſiders the great diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour that his raſh Oaths offer to the Name of God, and that Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Miſery muſt be his Puniſhment; unleſs he repents, he muſt needs ſure be toucht with a Sence of his Guilt and Danger, and theſe muſt certainly argue very ſtrongly with him to renounce 'em.</p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:135637:25"/>
               <p>Speaking Truth is likewiſe a very great <note place="margin">Truth in ſpeaking, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaking occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> means to reſtrain us from raſh Oaths when Men once come to be obſervable fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> their Truth and Integrity, there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> no need of an Oath to confirm th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Veracity of what they ſay; we ought alſo to avoid all occaſions that are moſt liable to betray us to this Vice, to preſerve conſtantly a deep and profound Veneration for the <note place="margin">Reverence to God.</note> Name of God, which we ſhould never men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion without Reſpect, and that wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> be an excellent means to prevent us againſt the prophaning it with ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Oaths.</p>
               <p>Another great means to reſtrain us from raſh Oaths, is to keep <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſtrict and conſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Watch over o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <note place="margin">Watchful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Prayer.</note> Words, and then t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> uſe the great reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of all Prayer, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> God would enable thee to avoid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:135637:25"/> overcome this wicked Cuſtom. And thus by theſe ſeveral ways of diſhonouring God's Name, we may eaſily perceive what it is to Honour it, <note place="margin">What it is to Honour God's Name.</note> which is all founded upon an awful Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect and Reverence, which is due to that ſacred Name, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat is Great, Wonderful and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="part">
               <head>PARTITION V.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of Worſhip due to God's Name, of Prayer, and its ſeveral Parts, of Publick Prayers in the Church, of Private Prayers, of Repentance, &amp;c. of Faſting.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THE next great <note place="margin">Worſhip.</note> Duty to God is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orſhip, a Duty only peculiar to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>mſelf, and therefore of a very <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reat Importance; and is to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rm'd, Firſt, By our Souls; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>econdly, By our Bodies, the Souls
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:135637:26"/> part is Praying, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of that there are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers <note place="margin">Prayer its Parts.</note> Parts, according to the different thing for which we aſk.</p>
               <p>Confeſſion is th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> firſt, and may be ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <note place="margin">Confeſſion.</note> general or pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, the former is a neceſſar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> part of our ſolemn Prayers, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Private or Publick; and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> latter more proper for the Private and the intent of it is, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſhould humble our ſelves before God, and with a deep and hear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Sorrow bewail the Sins we confeſs.</p>
               <p>The ſecond part <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Prayer is Petition, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <note place="margin">Petitions for our ſouls and bodies.</note> which we beg of Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> whatſoever we wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> either for our Soul or Bodies. For our Souls, we b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Pardon of our Sins, and the A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance of his Grace to enable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to obey his Will. For our Bodie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> we beg the neceſſaries of Life, ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> outward things I mean, that he his Wiſdom ſees moſt fit and nee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ful for us.</p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:135637:26"/>
               <p>A third part of Prayer is Deprecati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <note place="margin">Deprecation of Sin and Puniſhment.</note> by which we in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat God that he would turn away from us the evil of our Sins, and the Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments due to them; that he would prevent us from all Sin, and enable us againſt all Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and that he would forbear to chaſtize us with Spiritual or Temporal Puniſhments.</p>
               <p>The next part of Prayer is Interceſſion, <note place="margin">Interceſſion.</note> which conſiſt in Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for others, both for Strangers and Acquaintance, but in a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Manner for the Governours of the Church and State, and for our Relations and Friends.</p>
               <p>Another Part of Prayer is Thankſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, <note place="margin">Thankſgiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Mercies and tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral.</note> which is the praiſing and magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying God for all his Mercies both Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al and Temporal; for the bleſſings of our Souls and Bodies,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:135637:27"/> but above all for the ſending his Son to redeem us, and the Holy Ghoſt to comfort us, and for all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his Favours vouchſaf'd to us in his Word and Sacraments.</p>
               <p>Theſe are the ſeveral ſorts of Prayer to be uſed both Publick and Private, <note place="margin">Publick Prayer in the Church, and in the Family.</note> The Publick uſe of them is firſt in the Church, from whence we muſt not abſent our ſelves without ſome neceſſary Cauſe; and Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, In our own Families, where e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Maſter is ſtrictly bound to call his Children and Servants to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> daily exerciſe of them.</p>
               <p>Private Prayer, is call'd ſo, becauſe we <note place="margin">Private Prayer.</note> uſe it in Secret, where we have an oppotuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to be more particular than <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> convenient in Publick, and upon n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> account or pretence whatſoever <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to be omitted.</p>
               <p>Prayer is a Duty, that require<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a frequent performance by none ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domer
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:135637:27"/> then Evening and Morning; we <note place="margin">Frequent Prayer very advantage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</note> ſhould always begin and end the Day with our Addreſſes to Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, oftner if we have any conveniency, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed did we conſider the advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of Prayer, we ſhould think it great Wiſdom to uſe it as frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as poſſible.</p>
               <p>For Firſt, 'Tis a <note place="margin">Its Honour, Benefit and Pleaſantneſs</note> great Honour, that ſuch mean and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible Wretches as we are, ſhould be admitted but to ſpeak to the great God of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth; and then 'tis a Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit, the higheſt that can be Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin'd Prayer being that immediate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ource of all the Advantages we ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther want or wiſh, beſides 'tis a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>leaſant Duty in it ſelf, and to a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ruly Pious and Devout Mind, it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ffords abundance of ſubſtantial De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ight and Satisfaction.</p>
               <p>The Carnal Minds indeed can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſcover none of theſe Advantages,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:135637:28"/> the Pleaſures of the the Fleſh, and the <note place="margin">Carnality and want of uſe the Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes that makes it ſeem other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways.</note> droſs of the World li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in the way, and thoſe have ſo vitiated their Pallates, that they ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> taſte none of the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantneſs in it; other think it unpleaſant for want of a frequent uſage, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide theſe two, there is nothing ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> diſſuade us from the real Pleaſure and Advantage of it.</p>
               <p>The next thing is, how well w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> perform this Duty, and herein w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> are chiefly concern'd for the Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of our Prayer we are to aſk nothing <note place="margin">To ask no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, but with Faith, Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility and Attention.</note> unjuſt or unlawfu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> but all with Faith, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Humility, and wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the moſt profou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and deliberate Atte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>Oppoſite to Attention in Praye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is all wandring thoughts; the Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence of which are very dang<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous. To ſuppreſs theſe, we ſhould
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:135637:28"/> conſider the greatneſs of that Majeſty to <note place="margin">Help againſt Wandering the Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Gods Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty and our own needs.</note> whom we are ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the worth of thoſe things we aſk for, and our own ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Wants together.</p>
               <p>We muſt likewiſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nvoke God's Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tance, <note place="margin">To pray for God's aid with Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, Zeal Purity; and for proper ends.</note> and ſet a care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ul Watch over our Hearts to keep all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>andring thoughts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut of our Minds, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hilſt we are conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with Him; all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ur Petitions ſhould be put up to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>im with the higheſt Zeal and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ency of Soul; Our Prayers ſhould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e abſtracted from all manner of in and Impurity, and be conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> directed to right and proper ends.</p>
               <p>This is the firſt part of Worſhip, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he next is Bodily Worſhip, and this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt, <note place="margin">Bodily Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</note> in humble and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erend Geſtures in
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:135637:29"/> making our approaches to God, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſuch a decent lowlineſs of Body, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> may beſt declare with what a Pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtration of Soul, we make our Addre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſes before the Throne of Grace.</p>
               <p>Repentance is th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> next Duty we owe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <note place="margin">Repentance a turning from Sin to God, this Duty to be done dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</note> God, and is in ſho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> nothing elſe but a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Reſolution t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> forſake our Sins, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to implore his Grace the times for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> great Duty are as often as we thin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> upon our Sins; every Day at lea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> we ought to call our ſelves to a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> account.</p>
               <p>At ſome particula<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> times indeed, we a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <note place="margin">At ſet times, at the time of Affliction, at Death.</note> oblig'd to redoub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> our Repentance, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> thoſe Times we oug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> to fix for our ſelve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> at leaſt once a Week. We ought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> have a ſet time of Evening our Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts with God and our Conſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, the time of Affliction an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Calamity is a very proper ſeaſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:135637:29"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or it, and at our Death we are the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſt ſolemnly oblig'd to renew it.</p>
               <p>But 'tis dangerous <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> defer it till Death, <note place="margin">The danger and diſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of Death-bed Repentance.</note> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſhould not hazard <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Souls upon ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>certainties; beſide, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Death-bed Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance muſt conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uently want ſeveral Qualifications <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hich the Nature of true Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nce requires; the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſtom of Sin is not <note place="margin">The Cuſtom of Sin hard to be van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſh't. Pain the Cauſe of Inſincerity.</note> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> be deſtroy'd in a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> days, or hours, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>haps moments, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſides too, our Pains <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d Agonies moſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>obably diſturb our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>houghts, and then our Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nce can never be dreſs'd up with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>at ſtrict Sincerity, which God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ires of us for the Salvation of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Souls.</p>
               <p>To Repentance, the Duty of Faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>g may with great Reaſon be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ex'd which is a Duty we find ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>mnly recommended by God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:135637:30"/> the Church and the Practice of goo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <note place="margin">Faſting, a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge upon our ſelves, acceptable to God, yet no ſatisfaction for Sin.</note> Men; by Faſting, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in ſome meaſure r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge the Injuri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> done to God up<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> our ſelves, and ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Holy Revenge upo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> our ſelves for o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Sins, is doubtleſs very acceptable t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> God, and yet we ought not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> think them ſufficient without th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Merits of Chriſt's Blood to atton<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for our Offences.</p>
               <p>The Scripture h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> indeed given no pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular <note place="margin">Times of Faſting.</note> Direction, ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> often this great Du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of Faſting is to be perform'd, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the oftner the better; for being great Inſtrument of our Humilia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, we ought to take all opportu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to perform it, which our Heal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and Circumſtances will admit.</p>
               <p>And thus I have paſs'd throu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the the firſt Branch of our Duty <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> God to wit, the acknowledg i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> him to be our God; the ſecond
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:135637:30"/> the having no other, and of this I need ſay no more, then that by it we are forbid all kind of Idolatry and Superſtitious Worſhipping of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mages of Creatures, and all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ard Idolatry of the Mind.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="part">
               <head>PARTITION VI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of Sobriety, of Humility, the great Sin of Pride, of vain Glory, the Danger, Folly, the means to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent it, of Meekneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <head>Duty to our Selves.</head>
               <p>THis Duty to our <note place="margin">Duty to our Selves.</note> Selves, is by St. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aul</hi> ſumm'd up in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> word <hi>SOBERLY,</hi> by which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> meaning muſt be our keeping <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ithin thoſe bounds which God has <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> us, both with reſpect to our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ouls and Bodies; and this ſober <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>overnment of the Soul requires a
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:135637:31"/> great many <hi>Vertues,</hi> of which I place Humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty <note place="margin">Humility.</note> in the firſt Rank.</p>
               <p>Humility gives us low and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thoughts of our ſelves, direct us to behave our ſelves eaſily und<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the mean Opinion of others, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> withal is directly oppoſite to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> kind of Pride, and vain Glory; tw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the moſt dangerous Enemies <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Mankind.</p>
               <p>Pride in the fir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Place, is a very gre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <note place="margin">Pride a great Sin, betraies us to other Sins, fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates all Remedies. Expoſes us to Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> and provoking Sin, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> has been often ſhe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> by God's ſevere P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>niſhments of it, it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in ſome reſpects, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ther a Parent or Nurſe to moſt oth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Vices, by betrayi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> us firſt, and then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> drawing us in to reject all Remed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and by fruſtrating all the deſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and overtures of Gods Mercies; a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> beſide this too, it betrays us to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>niſhments, God having all al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> declar'd himſelf the proud Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> particular Enemy.</p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:135637:31"/>
               <p>'Tis likewiſe a very fooliſh Vice, a Vice <note place="margin">The Folly of Pride in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the Goods of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, Fortune or Grace.</note> that argues the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Folly that can be, becauſe there can be nothing either in the Goods of Nature, Fortune or Grace, that with any reaſonable pretence we can be proud of.</p>
               <p>That this dangerous and fooliſh Sin is to be avoided, I ſuppoſe we may take for granted, and the chief Means to do it, are by applying our ſelves to God for the Grace of Humility; <note place="margin">Means of Humility.</note> which may be beſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quir'd by a Reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on upon our own Sins, Follies, Meanneſs and Imperfections; to which we ought to joyn our hearty Prayers, that God would make us ſome of thoſe poor in Spirit to whom the Bleſſings of Heaven are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis'd.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Vain Glory; that is, an empty thirſt after the Praiſe of Men, is likewiſe oppoſite to Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:135637:32"/> and a very great Sin; for it betraies <note place="margin">Vain Glory; the Sin, Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of it.</note> Men into ſeveral dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, but more eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially erraces Chriſt out of their Heart<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 'Tis an Indication of Folly too, which every one muſt be ſatisfied in, that would but conſider what 'tis he hunts for, only a little emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Applauſe, a little popular Air<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which can never bring him any ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid advantage; the Means to help this <note place="margin">Helps a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Vain-Glory.</note> are to conſider o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſelves in the firſt place and then the true ſtate of things in the ſecond, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> weigh both in the Ballance of Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Sobriety.</p>
               <p>Meekneſs; that is a Calm and peacef<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <note place="margin">Meekneſs and the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages of it.</note> Temper is another great Vertue, and may be exerciſed both with reſpect to God and our ſelves, that towards God falls under the Head of Humility
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:135637:32"/> and is already ſpoken to; as it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects our ſelves, 'tis an Advantage in a great many Particulars; more eſpecially as it promotes our Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Reputation, enables us to bear the Sufferings of Humane Life with Eaſe and Moderation, and with Prudence and a good poſture of Mind; and the proper Means to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <note place="margin">Means of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining it</note> this moſt admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Vertue, are by comparing the Lovelineſs and Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits of it, with the uglineſs and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs of Rage and Anger, but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all, by contemplating the Life and Example of that great Pattern of all Meekneſs <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Conſideration is a third Vertue, that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates <note place="margin">Conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our ſtate, 'tis the rule to try our State.</note> to the Soul, and directs us to prepon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate both our State and our Actions; to weigh our State firſt, and to conſider both the Grounds of our Faith, and the Caſe of our Souls; and accordingly to prepare
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:135637:33"/> our ſelves againſt the Day of Deat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and Judgment; an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the neglect of thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <note place="margin">The Danger of Inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</note> moſt excellent Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue has been the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine of thouſands, and is the general Cauſe of all our Sin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and Misfortunes.</p>
               <p>It directs us too i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> our Actions; teache<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <note place="margin">Of our Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons before, and after we do them.</note> us to adviſe with ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Conſciences, and t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> debate the probabl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> good or ill of every thing we do before we do it, and t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> examine likewiſe thoſe things tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> we have already done, whether they may be warranted by the Law<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of God, and the Rules of Religio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and Sobriety; upon many Account<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> therefore we are to employ it often both with reſpect to our State an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Actions, and to mak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> up our Accounts fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently; <note place="margin">Frequency of Conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it.</note> and the plain Reaſon for it i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> this, becauſe ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Lives are ſo waver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:135637:33"/> and uncertain, that we hazard our Salvation, when ever we lie down to ſleep in an unrepented Sin.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="part">
               <head>PARTITION VII</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of Contentedneſs, and the contraries to it; Murmurings, Ambition, Covetouſneſs, Envy; Helps to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentedneſs; of Duties which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern our Bodies; of Chaſtity, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Helps to it; of Temperance.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THE next Duty <note place="margin">Contentment</note> to our ſelves is contentedneſs, which conſiſts in an evenneſs and an humble acquieſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe under any State it ſhall pleaſe God to allot for us; and without this, 'tis impoſſible we ſhould be in any tolerable Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Happineſs. The <note place="margin">The contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, murmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs.</note> Contraries to it, are Murmurings and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patience under God's Diſpenſations, all Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:135637:34"/> Thoughts and Deſires, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> all ſorts of Covetouſneſs, Griping<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and Extortions.</p>
               <p>Covetouſneſs is a very great and high <note place="margin">Covetouſneſs contrary to our Duty to God, our Selves, and our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours.</note> Offence, and direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly oppoſite to the great Duties we owe to God, our Selves and our Neighbours<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 'tis oppoſite to our Duty to God, by ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king our Minds off from him, and embaraſing them with the Cares and Troubles of the World; 'tis oppoſite to our Duties to our Selves, both with regard to our Souls and Bodies by urging us to ſacrifice the firſt to a little Pelf and Droſs, and the latter to Pains and Diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and ſo 'tis oppoſite to our Duties to our Neighbours, both in our Juſtice and Charity, by forcing us upon unlawful Means, and by ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting us upon falſe and indirect meaſures; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentedneſs <note place="margin">Contented<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs contrary to Envy.</note> is alſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to all kind of
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:135637:34"/> Envy and Malice, and can never in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habit in any Breaſt, that is the leaſt tinctur'd with Prejudice or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge.</p>
               <p>Helps for Content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <note place="margin">Helps to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment.</note> are the Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of God's Goodneſs, Power, and Juſtice, and his univerſal Care of the World, that all our Affairs are in his hand who knows our Wants better than our ſelves; Secondly, We ſhould conſider the Vanity of all earthly things, by comparing them with the eſſential Joys of Heaven; that we are here but as Strangers and Pilgrims, and that whatever our outward Condition may be, there's a time coming when we ſhall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver'd from the burthen of all our Sins and Sorrows. and be enſtated in a Happineſs large as our Wiſh and laſting as our Souls.</p>
               <p>A Fifth Duty is Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, which is a <note place="margin">Diligence. It conſiſts in Watchfulneſs and Induſtry to improve the Gifts of Nature and Grace.</note> Duty which we like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe owe to our Souls by watching carefully
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:135637:35"/> over them, and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently guarding the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> againſt all Dangers, and then improving them induſtriouſly in every Vertue, and in all the Gift<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Nature, and the accompliſhments of Grace.</p>
               <p>We muſt likewiſe improve and cheriſh <note place="margin">Good Moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prov'd, the danger of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ing them</note> all good Motions, and make the moſt of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Holy Suggeſtion, leſt upon our diſpiſing the overtures of Grace, God withdraws from us all manner of kindneſs, and turns us up to a reprobate Sence; and thus far of the Vertues which belong to our Souls, I come next to thoſe that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to our Bodies.</p>
               <p>In the front of theſe I place Chaſtity, a <note place="margin">Chaſtity, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bids all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſs.</note> Vertue which ſtrictly forbids all manner of wantonneſs and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſs, not only the groſſer Acts of Adultery and
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:135637:35"/> Fornication, but likewiſe all impure Thoughts, and all unchaſt Looks and Geſtures.</p>
               <p>The Beauty of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtity <note place="margin">The miſchief of it, both to Body and Soul, and God's Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments againſt it.</note> can be no how better deſcrib'd, then by comparing it with the loathſomeneſs of Luſt, and the many E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils and miſchiefs that ſpring from it. Luſt defaces the Dignity of our very Souls, and ſinks the rational Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture into a Bruit; it makes our Minds foul and filty, and loads our Bodies with Diſeaſes and Deformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and what's worſt of all, does generally call down Gods great and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy <note place="margin">It ſhuts us out from Heaven.</note> Judgments upon us, and ſhuts the Gare of Heaven againſt us Eternally.</p>
               <p>Theſe and many other are the ſad effects of Uncleanneſs, againſt which we <note place="margin">Helps to Chaſtity.</note> ought to fortifie our ſelves, by avoiding I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleneſs,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:135637:36"/> and improving our Mind in all kind of active Vertue; by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voiding all manner of Temptation and all leud Company, but above all, by praying earneſtly, that God would give us a Spirit of Purity.</p>
               <p>The ſecond Vertue relating to our Bodie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <note place="margin">Temperance in Eating.</note> is Temperance, and the Exerciſes of tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> are divers, <hi>i. e.</hi> in Eating, Drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Sleeping, Recreation, and Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parel; I ſhall ſpeak of them ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately, and begin with Eating.</p>
               <p>Temperance in Eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, is then obſerved <note place="margin">The ends of it to preſerve Life and Health.</note> when we make it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to the end for which God and Nature deſign'd i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to wit, the Preſervation of Life and Health; thoſe are the ſole end of it, and he that propoſes it either to gratifie his Taſte, or Pamper h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Body, Croſſes Gods original Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe in it, and breaks all the Rule of Temperance by which it ſhould be regulated; nay, he Sacrifice
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:135637:36"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll his other Sences to his Taſte, expoſes <note place="margin">Rules for Temperance, and the means of it.</note> himſelf to the Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter of a Glutton, and what's worſt of all, to the Fate of that rich Glutton, that after all his Dainties wanted at laſt a drop of Water to cool his Tongue.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="part">
               <head>PARTITION VIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of Temperance in Drinking; falſe ends of Drinking, <hi>viz.</hi> Good Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip, putting away Cares,</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THE next thing <note place="margin">Drinking directed to falſe Ends.</note> is Temperance in Drinking; the right Ends whereof are the very ſame with Eating, <hi>viz.</hi> the preſerving our Lives and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting our Healths, but this like the former has been ſadly ſubvert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and directed to Purpoſes ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſtant from the Original intent of it.</p>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:135637:37"/>
               <p>Men now drink themſelves into Beaſt <note place="margin">Falſe end of Drinking, Good-Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip.</note> under the common but falſe Notion of Good-Fellowſhip; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers drink to exceſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> under the pretence that 'tis a gre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> means to maintain a mutual Friendſhip <note place="margin">Preſerving Kindneſs. Chearing the Spirits, and putting away Cares.</note> and Correſponden<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> amongſt Men; ſome will have it, that 'tis highly uſeful to che<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the Spirits, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> correct and diſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Melancholy; that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> drives away the Cares and Perple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xities of Humane Life; that 'tis very fit for the paſſing away time and filling up empty Intervals, na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſome will tell us 'tis Reproach not to d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <note place="margin">Preventing Reproach.</note> it, and argues a great deal of ſowreneſs and diſingenuity, man there are that drink <note place="margin">Pleaſure of Drinking.</note> for drinking ſake that love the Liquor
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:135637:37"/> and ſo are Sots without any of the former Pretences; but theſe are all great miſtakes, and truly upon a fair State of the Matter, 'tis a ſubject fit both for our Wonder and Sorrow, how this unaccountable Practice of exceſſive Drinking ſhould have ſo unluckily encroach'd upon all Societies; that no Bargain can be made <note place="margin">Bargaining.</note> (which is another pretence for it) nor nothing of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Moment tranſacted, but the Tavern, or the Ale-houſe muſt be the Place fixt upon for the doing of it.</p>
               <p>The unreaſonable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs <note place="margin">Degrees of this Sin.</note> of theſe Motives is too plain to admit of a Diſpute, they are all ſo ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, abſurd and inconſiſtent, that upon a ſhort Appeai to common Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience we find 'em exploded and condemn'd; every Degree of this Sin is a high breach of Temperance; every drop we drink beyond what is convenient for moderate Refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, is an Offence both againſt
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:135637:38"/> God and Man, and the ſtrong Drinke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <note place="margin">The great Guilt of ſtrong drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers:</note> above all the reſt both from the evi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of his Example, and Practice the moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>accountable.</p>
               <p>A Man would think that the many Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs <note place="margin">The great Miſchiefs of the Sin, an Exhortation to forſake it.</note> that attend this Sin ſhould be a warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to us to avoid it when we conſider 'tis a diſhonour to God a reproach to Chriſtianity, and a Deſtruction both to our Souls and Bodies; ſure a few Exhortations may ſerve to prevail with us to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake it.</p>
               <p>And why ſhould any ſeeming diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties <note place="margin">Difficulties of forſaking it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider'd, <hi>viz.</hi> Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of drink, want of employ and Reproaches and Perſuaſions of Men.</note> diſſuade us againſt parting with ſo dangerous a Vice; why ſhould we plead Cuſtom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> or the Neceſſity of Drink, or why
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:135637:38"/> ſhould we betray ſo much Folly, nay ſo much Wickedneſs to make drinking the buſineſs of our Lives. Alas! 'tis a miſtake, and let the vain deluded Drunkard ſay what he will, it can be no Reproach to us to reject all Intemperances of this kind, and all the Perſuaſions of Men upon that Account.</p>
               <p>The Means to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt theſe, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <note place="margin">Means to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt this Sin, by weighing the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage with the hurt, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecting the Temptations.</note> Temptations for intemperate Drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, are to weigh the Good with the Ill, and the pretended Advantages with the real Loſſes and Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and to reject them at their very <note place="margin">Security to do ſo. Love of the Sin hinders the means, makes Men loath to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the danger.</note> beginnings, and to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void all manner of Occaſions and Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities, this we may do, if it be not our own fault, and theſe and ſuch like means will effectually do the
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:135637:39"/> Buſineſs, if our miſtaken Love t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Vice does not hinder it, and make us unwilling to believe it, either dangerous or deſtructive.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="part">
               <head>PARTITION IX:</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Temperance in Sleep; the Rule of i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Miſchiefs of Sloth, of Recreations Cautions to be obſerv'd in them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Apparel.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>SLeep is a Thin <note place="margin">Sleep.</note> part of Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, which is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, <note place="margin">The Rule of Temperance therein; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Sins fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the Tranſgreſſion of it, with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niencies.</note> if meaſur'd b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the end for which God ordain'd it, only for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Refreſhment; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſupport for our frai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Bodies; and in this we are likewiſe to take Care not to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulge our ſelves to far leaſt at length it encline us to Sloth which is ordinarily attended with a whole train of dangerous Sins, and
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:135637:39"/> with abundance of other great In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniencies.</p>
               <p>We ſhould likewiſe <note place="margin">Temperance in Recreati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> have a very high re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to Temperance in our Recreations, and be perpetually <note place="margin">Cautions to be obſerv'd.</note> Cautious, that they are lawful in their kind, and no ways diſhonourable to God, or Injurious to our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour; we ſhould be very careful too, that they never <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>end to undue Ends, <note place="margin">
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndue Ends of Sports.</note> but are all exactly In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent, harmleſs and inoffenſive.</p>
               <p>The laſt part of <note place="margin">Temperance in Apparel.</note> Temperance is that of Apparel, and this as well as the reſt is to be meaſured according to the Ends for which Cloathing was ordain'd; which were firſt to provide a modeſt and decent covering to hide our Naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, this was the firſt and great End of it; the ſecond was to fence our Bodies from the Severities of
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:135637:40"/> the Cold, and ſecure to us ſuch a conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent <note place="margin">Apparel de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd for a covering of ſhame.</note> Warmth that is neceſſary for the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of our Health; and the third for the diſtinguiſhing <note place="margin">Fencing from Cold.</note> Perſons both with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to their Sex, and Qualities. Now theſe are the three grand Ends of our Apparel, which we ſhould always be careful to preſerve i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <note place="margin">Diſtinction of Perſons.</note> the middle, between the extreams of gau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſs and contempt.</p>
               <p>And thus I have paſs'd through the ſeveral Branches of Temperance and herein I would in no reſpect ſeem to advance a contrary ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream; <hi>i. e.</hi> too much ſparingneſs, which is <note place="margin">Too much ſparing, a fault as well as Exceſs.</note> indeed a fault as well as Exceſs. A Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous griping Temper is no more to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted for, then any of the form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; and is in many Particulars a
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:135637:40"/> high breach of our Duty both to God, our Selves, and our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="part">
               <head>PARTITION X.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of Duty's to our Neighbours. Of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, Negative, Poſitive, of the Sin of Murther, of the Hainouſneſs of it, the Puniſhment of it, and the ſtrange Diſcoveries thereof. Of Maiming, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <head>Duties to our Neighbours.</head>
               <p>IN the Word Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs <note place="margin">Duties to our Neighbour—Juſtice.</note> are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd in groſs the Duties to our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour; and in the larger Sence it contains all kind, both of Juſtice and Charity. I begin with Juſtice, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f which there is two ſorts, Nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive and Poſitive.</p>
               <p>By Negative Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, <note place="margin">Negative Juſtice.</note> we are forbid to do any wrong to
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:135637:41"/> any Man; either in reſpect to hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Soul, Body, his Poſſeſſions, or his Credit; and firſt we muſt not do a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny manner of Injury to the Soul, either in <note place="margin">To the Soul in the Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Sence.</note> a Natural and Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Sence; we mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> take great Care that we give no occaſion <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Grief or Sadneſs to the Mind of an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Man, in which Sence the Soul <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſaid to be naturally injur'd; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> alike diligent not to adminiſter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> him the Cauſe, either of Sin or Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, in which Caſe the So<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> may be ſpiritually wrong'd.</p>
               <p>Sin is the Diſea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and Wound of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <note place="margin">Drawing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Sin, a great Injury.</note> Soul, and the ſed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> cing us to it is t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> greateſt Injury th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> can be done us. There are ſever<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Means for this, both direct and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> direct; the direct Means are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> commanding us, coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelling, enticing <note place="margin">Direct and indirect means of it.</note> aſſiſting us; the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> direct Means by ſhe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:135637:41"/> us ill Examples, or by incoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging us in any Wickedneſs; by ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifying Vice, and by throwing Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach upon the Duties, and ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Religion, and by theſe, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ch like Means, both direct and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>direct, Men bring upon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the great guilt of injuring <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d wounding their Brethrens <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ouls.</p>
               <p>It would be too <note place="margin">This ſort of Injury Men ought ſadly to conſider, to bewail and repair.</note> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ng to inſtance, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>veral Sins by which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>en enſnare others: will therefore leave with this Caution, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>at it concerns them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> near as their Souls, to conſider that Injuries they have done of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>is kind, and to bewail them with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e deepeſt Concern and Sorrow; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>id not only that neither, but as a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ore particular Teſtimony of their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>pentance, to do their beſt by all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e means they can to make Repa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tion.</p>
               <p>Negative Juſtice in the ſecond <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ce binds us againſt all kind of
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:135637:42"/> Injury to the Bodies more eſpecially a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <note place="margin">Negative Juſtice in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the Life.</note> the Life of our Brethren. Murth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> is a Sin of the de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Dye, and may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> committed either openly and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> rectly, or elſe ſecretly and treach<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> rouſly. It may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> done, either by op<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <note place="margin">Several ways of being guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</note> and Publick Violen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> or elſe effected und<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the Coverture of con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ceal'd Malice and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, but which way ſoever it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Sin is of that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> alted hainouſneſs, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <note place="margin">The hainouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Sin, and the Puniſhments of it.</note> it provokes God to higher degree of A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in the Execut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> of his Vengeance <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Puniſhments upon than any other Vice in all the b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> and dreadful Catalogue.</p>
               <p>It is worth our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice by what mira<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous <note place="margin">The ſtrange diſcoveries of it.</note> Means God been pleas'd to di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:135637:42"/> ver it; and indeed would we but take <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to our ſerious Thoughts, it muſt needs poſſeſs us with the greateſt Horrour and Abomination of it, and engage us to watch and guard <note place="margin">We muſt Watch a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches.</note> our ſelves againſt the moſt diſtant approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of this Vice.</p>
               <p>Next to the Murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, the maiming and <note place="margin">Maiming, an Injury which every Man dreads.</note> diſabling our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour is a very great Sin, this we muſt grant, by reflecting <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ow precious our Limbs are, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ow miſerable a thing the want of any of 'em is; eſpecially, if it be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> poor Man; in ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Caſe, though we <note place="margin">Worſt in a poor Man.</note> can never make him a full Satisfaction, we are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he moſt ſolemnly <note place="margin">A neceſſity of Satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ound to provide for his own, and his Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ies wants.</p>
               <p>Unlawful Wounds and Stripes are likewiſe highly inconſiſtent with
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:135637:43"/> that golden Rule of Loving our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour <note place="margin">Wounds and Stripes inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious alſo.</note> as our Selves and indeed our Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty to others, argu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> not only a great de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <note place="margin">Cruelty to others the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of Pride</note> of Pride and In<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, but withal <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſavageneſs and brui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſhneſs of mind, much below the common tenderneſs and compaſſion that becomes the humane Nature.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="part">
               <head>PARTITION XI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of Juſtice about the Poſſeſſions of o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Neighbours; againſt injuring hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in his Wife, his Goods; of Oppre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; Theft; of paying of Debt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>THE next part <note place="margin">His Poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> Negative Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, relates to the Poſſeſſions of our Neighbours, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the front of which we may wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> great Reaſon place the Wife. O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:135637:43"/> Wives, are the Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple part of our Poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, <note place="margin">The Wife; the enticing her, great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice to the Woman and the Man.</note> and the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupting Her to defile Her Huſbands bed, is the worſt and higheſt part of Injuſtice both to the Man and the Woman; this is an ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reparable <note place="margin">The moſt Ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reparable.</note> ſort of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury. A Vice that God has declar'd that he himſelf will Judge, and we may depend upon't, without Repentance that Judgment of his will be the moſt ſevere and dreadful.</p>
               <p>Next to this, we owe a Nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Juſtice to our Neighbour with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſpect to his Goods; ſuch as are his Houſe, <note place="margin">His Goods.</note> Land, Cattel, Money, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c. and the two ordinary Cauſes that engages Men to break it, are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ther Malice or Covetouſneſs.</p>
               <p>That Part of Injuſtice that is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>unded upon pure Malice, is commonly <note place="margin">Malicious Injuſtice.</note> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>cted upon the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:135637:44"/> Principle, like him they ſeek to deſtroy others; not ſo much, as 'tis any good to themſelves, but out of a natural deſire to do miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief, the other part that is found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon Covetouſneſs, though indeed it may <note place="margin">Covetous In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice.</note> have ſomething of a baſe and ſordid De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign in it; yet when 'tis conſidered, 'tis always attended by Oppreſſion Theft and Deceit, it wants very little to come up to the wickedneſs of the former.</p>
               <p>Oppreſſion is an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolent bare-fac'd Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery, <note place="margin">Oppreſſion and Gods Vengeance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it.</note> and ſo much the worſe ſtill, becauſe the Poor are general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Perſons injur'd we have many. Lectures againſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very kind of it, in Holy Scripture<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> but eſpecially againſt that which affects the Fatherleſs and Widdow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 'tis indeed a moſt crying guilt, and God's heavy Vengeance is no one inſtance more exemplary, he that has oppreſst the Poor; ſaith the
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:135637:44"/> Prophet, ſhall ſurely die, and his Blood ſhall be upon him.</p>
               <p>Theft is another kind of this Injuſtice, <note place="margin">Theft; not paying what we borrow, are bound for, or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe.</note> which in general is twofold, the firſt is the withholding what we ſhould pay, and the laſt the taking from our Neighbour what we have no Right too; the firſt as well as the laſt, is a plain Act of Robbery, and let the preſent Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of the World argue never ſo much for it, it can never prove, but that by common Juſtice and Hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty we are ſtrictly engag'd, to the utmoſt of our Abilities, to diſcharge all the debts we are oblig'd to, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by Bond, Promiſe, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther lawful Obligation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="part">
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:135637:45"/>
               <head>PARTITION XII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of Theft; Stealing; of Deceit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Truſt; in Traffick; of Reſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>THE next Par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <note place="margin">Stealing the Goods of our Neighbour.</note> of Theft is; ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by open Violen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> or private Fraud, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Robbing our Neighbour of tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> which he is in Poſſeſſion of. This a Vice that wants no Aggravation it need not be diſputed, but th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> both the High-way Man and Houſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> breaker, as well as the ſly, injurio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Pilferer are two Ranks of degen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Creatures ſo odious to God that they are unfit for humane S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety. There are a great ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Branches of this ſort of Robber<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> as the Concealing of ſtol'n Good<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the buying them at cheap Rate with many others, which I need n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> mention any further, they being beſt but a kind of Robbery. God
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:135637:45"/> will be ſure to deal ſeverely with us upon that account, although perhaps we may eſcape the Cogui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ance of the Law.</p>
               <p>A third Part of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice is Deceit, of <note place="margin">Deceit.</note> which the Acts are ſo numerous, that 'tis morally impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to Name 'em all: I ſhall Rank them therefore under theſe two ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Heads, <hi>viz.</hi> The Deceits of Truſt, and Traffick.</p>
               <p>He that deceives a Man in a Matter of <note place="margin">In Truſt.</note> Truſt that is commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to him, is guilty of the moſt treacherous and baſe Injuſtice; in ſuch a Caſe we are to behave our ſelves with the utmoſt Fidelity; eſpecially, when any thing for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſes of Piety or Charity are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to our Charge; he that vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lates his Faith in theſe particulars, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dds Sacriledge to Fraud and Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hery, and entails upon him all the Curſes that are due to thoſe Sins.</p>
               <p>As to Matters of Traffick, there
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:135637:46"/> may be deceit both in the Buyer and Seller; <note place="margin">In Traffick. By the Sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers conceal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the faults, and over-rating their Wares.</note> the Seller Sins great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, when by a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nection of Lies, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps Oaths and Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crations, he conceals or excuſes the faults in his Commodities, or what's as bad, ſells by falſe weights and meaſures, or impoſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> an extravagant unreaſonable Price upon the Buyer; theſe are indeed grown very common and practic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> faults, but yet never the more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſable, the great Judge of Truth and Equity has often declar'd his ſolemn diſpleaſure againſt 'em, and will be ſure, ſooner or later, to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh them to the utmoſt.</p>
               <p>The Buyer may be guilty of Fraud too <note place="margin">Fraud in the Buyer.</note> and though indeed h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> does not fall under ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> many Temptations as the Seller yet when ever he makes an advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of his Neighbours Wants, and Purchaſes his Commodities at un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:135637:46"/> Rates, without doubt he offends the Juſtice of God, by thus inſult<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon, and making his Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of his Brothers Neceſſities.</p>
               <p>The Temptations to Deceit in Traffick, <note place="margin">Many Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit in Traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fick.</note> are ſo interwoven with all Trades, that it behoves every deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Man to have a great Care to guard himſelf againſt them, this way of Cheating is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a perfect Trade it ſelf, and Men boaſt of it, and value them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves upon it, but for all that the Eyes of God are too pure to behold ſuch Iniquity; nay, <note place="margin">The common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach to Chriſtianity.</note> 'tis even a ſcandal to our Chriſtian Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, a very high and ſolemn breach of thoſe common Rules of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and Equity laid down in the Precepts of the Goſpel to be the Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard and Guide of our Actions.</p>
               <p>Beſides all this, 'tis but a miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Principle neither, Fraud and Undermining, deceitful meaſures
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:135637:47"/> and falſe ballances are not the right way to <note place="margin">It is no way to make a Man Rich, but ruines the Soul.</note> make us Rich, there goes a ſecret Curſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long with ſuch kind of Practice which is generally executed in this Life; which though it may by chance fail here, it never fails in the next; there the Deceiver will be fatally deceiv'd in the loſs of his Soul, the Conſideration of which ſhould methinks put him upon the grand <note place="margin">Reſtitution.</note> Remedy, Reſtitution, without which he can never make any tolerable Attonement for the Injury he has done either to God or his Neighbour.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="part">
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:135637:47"/>
               <head>PARTITION XIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of falſe Reports; falſe Witneſs; Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Slanders, Wiſperings; of Scof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fing, Calamities, Sins, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive Juſtice, Truth, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ying, of Envy and Detraction, of Grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>THE Credit of <hi>His Credit.</hi> our Neighbour is another Part of Negative Juſtice, which ſhould be as dear to us as his Poſſeſſions, and ſhould in no reſpect be impair'd either by falſe Reports or malicious Surmizes and Conje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures, from both which our Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, the deareſt thing we have, next our Souls, is liable to great In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury.</p>
               <p>Falſe Reports may <note place="margin">Falſe Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</note> be ſpread divers ways, both Publick and Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate, the Publick way is ordinari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, by bearing falſe Witneſs either with regard to our Lives or Eſtates;
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:135637:48"/> this is a moſt grievous Wound in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed to our Credit, a ſort of out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious Injuſtice to our Neighbour, that we are hardly ever able to make him amends for.</p>
               <p>The ſecond open way of ſpread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theſe Reports is by Publick Slander, <note place="margin">Publick Slander.</note> and herein our Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation is alſo liable to a great deal of Injury. Reproaches, Lying, Scandal and Railing make up the baſe Compoſition, which as the Apoſtle long ago obſerv'd were amongſt other Works of the Fleſh, fit only to ſhut Men out of the Church here, and the Kingdom of Heaven hereafter.</p>
               <p>The Private way of ſpreading ſuch Reports is Whiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pering, this is a way as <note place="margin">Whiſpering.</note> dangerous if not worſt then the former, and is by St. <hi>Paul</hi> mention'd in the Catalogue of great Crimes, which are the effect of a Reprobate Mind; this is a kind of Slander that like ſecret Poyſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> deſtroys us inſenſibly; 'tis <hi>Solomon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:135637:48"/> Obſervation; that the Wiſperer ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parates chief Friends, than which nothing can argue louder for the ſuppreſſing of it.</p>
               <p>The ſeveral Steps <note place="margin">Several Steps toward this Sin.</note> of this Vice are to be carefully avoided, as Firſt, We ſhould be ſo far from encouraging it, that we ſhould rather reject the very firſt approaches of the Tale-bearer: Secondly, We ſhould be very Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious how we believe falſe Reports, or rather we ſhould never give any Credit at all to them: And Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, We ſhould be ſure never to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port any thing we here from ſuch kind of People, but look upon 'em no leſs Enemies to us, then to thoſe of whom they are ſpeaking.</p>
               <p>Beſides, this open way of impair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our Neighbours Credit, there is<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yet another, which though it may ſeem to be a little more plauſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, is yet in all reſpects as bad as the former; I mean Scoffing and Reviling, <note place="margin">Scoffing and Reviling.</note> which indeed is not
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:135637:49"/> only an Injury to our Neighbour, but even to God himſelf.</p>
               <p>The three Things for which Men are <note place="margin">For Infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, and Sins.</note> commonly revil'd, are either for their Infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, their Calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties or their Sins; and why ſhould Men be deſpis'd for that which they cannot help, this is calling God's Providence to an Account, eſpecially with reſpect to the two former; indeed for our Sins they have more of our Wills, 'tis true, but then conſidering they make us the moſt miſerable of any thing elſe, without doubt they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire a great deal of our Pity and Compaſſion.</p>
               <p>We owe likewiſe a Negative Juſtice to <note place="margin">Deſtroying the Credit, a great Injury, and irrepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable.</note> the Credit and Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour; his Credit is the moſt valuable thing he has, and therefore to Rob him of that, is the higheſt Injury we can do him
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:135637:49"/>
'tis the higheſt, becauſe his Damage is irreparable; the utmoſt we can do, can never make him amends, and yet <note place="margin">Every guilty Perſon to do all he can in Order to it.</note> we muſt do our beſt, becauſe without it we can never expect God's Pardon for the Sin.</p>
               <p>Thus I have paſt through the four Branches of Negative Juſtice to our Neighbour, and yet muſt further obſerve, that this Juſtice binds our <note place="margin">Juſtice in the Thoughts.</note> Thoughts as well as our Words and Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; nay, it confines even our Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes and Affections. Our whole Hearts ſhould be intent upon his Good, and our Minds conſtantly taken up, which way we may beſt promote the Happineſs both of his Soul and Body.</p>
               <p>I come <hi>now</hi> to ſpeak <note place="margin">Poſitive Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice.</note> of Poſitive Juſtice, by which is intended the giving to every Man his proper dues, whether General, or Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar;
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:135637:50"/> as Firſt, The ſpeaking Truth in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral <note place="margin">Speaking Truth, a due to all Men.</note> of all Mankind; this is a common debt we owe to every one, and indeed we are bound to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſtrict performance of it, by many ſtrong and weighty Obligations, but the greateſt of all is, becauſe Lying is a Vice ſo ſcandalous and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious in it ſelf, and ſo ſolemnly condemn'd in many parts of Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; <note place="margin">Lying forbid in Scripture.</note> but then whats very ſtrange, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding 'tis the moſt <note place="margin">Lying a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Sin.</note> fooliſh and ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, 'tis become ſo common, that 'tis a great Rariety (to uſe the Words of the Royal Prophet) to find a Man that ſpeaks the Truth from his Heart.</p>
               <p>Next to this we owe to all, Humanity<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <note place="margin">Courteſie due to all, yet un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paid by the Proud.</note> and a courteous and affable Behaviour, a Vertue which a Proud
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:135637:50"/> Man can never arrive to; he is ſo buſie in admiring himſelf, that he overlooks all the Perfections of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
               <p>Meekneſs is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe <note place="margin">Meekneſs, a due to all Men.</note> a Debt we owe to every Body, and indeed a very great accompliſhment, and highly neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for the Preſervation of the Peace of the World; whilſt on the contrary, all ſorts of Brawlings and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions, <note place="margin">Brawlingve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry unſuffera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and leads to the Sin of Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing.</note> tend to Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order and Confuſion, nay, what's worſe, they tend to a great many Sins too, but eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to that moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voking Sin, Curſing and Execra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>Having thus far <note place="margin">Particular Dues.</note> ſpoken of Dues in Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, I come now to the Particular, which Men are or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily entitl'd to upon ſome ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Qualification, the three chief are, that of Excellency, that of Want, and that of Relation.</p>
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:135637:51"/>
               <p>And firſt a Man is entitl'd to our Reſpect <note place="margin">A reſpect due to Men of extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Gifts.</note> upon the Account of his Excellency. I mean for his extraordinary Gifts and Endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, ſuch as are Wiſdom, Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Grace, and the like; and ſuch a Perſon we are in no reſpect either to Envy or Revile, or to grudge at God's <note place="margin">We are not to Envy them, nor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract from them.</note> Bleſſings and Kindneſs to him; we ſhould not attempt to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract from his Worth, or to cloud or dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en his Merits, but rather do our beſt to make 'em as conſpicuous as we can, and this we ſhould do not only as it is a Debt which we owe to him, but becauſe the contrary is an Act <note place="margin">The Folly of both theſe.</note> of extream folly, as well as ill Nature and Injuſtice.</p>
               <p>Beſide the Excellencies of the Mind, we owe a regard to the Quality and outward Advantages.
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:135637:51"/> God for the due go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verning of the World, <note place="margin">A reſpect due to Men in regard of their Ranks and Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</note> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>as decreed ſeveral Orders and Claſſes of Men, to each of which in Proportion to their reſpective Dignity we are to pay a due Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect.</p>
               <p>We are alſo Deb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors <note place="margin">Dues to thoſe that are in any ſort of Want, to the Poor.</note> to Perſons under any kind of Want, whether Spiritual or Temporal, but more eſpecially to the Poor, who by Gods particular Appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, have a ſolemn Right to our ſuperfluities; and then it can be nothing elſe but an arrant Robbery to beſtow that upon our Luſt or Vanity, which is aſſign'd for their Portion. In the Caſe of the Poor we are Gods Stewards, and 'tis the ſame unjuſtice and fraud for us to embezle that which he has entruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with us, as it is for any Steward to miſemploy that which was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for the uſe of his Maſters
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:135637:52"/> Family, and common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly too meets with the <note place="margin">God with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draws thoſe Abilities, that are not thus em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd.</note> Doom of the unjuſt Steward in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, to cauſe us to he put out of our Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardſhip, and have thoſe Abilities taken away, that have been ſo unfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully employ'd.</p>
               <p>The third Qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation is that of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, <note place="margin">Duties in reſpect to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation.</note> and of this there are divers ſorts, as Firſt, that of a Debtor to a Creditor, and of an oblig'd Perſon to his Benefactor, and in both theſe Particulars we are bound by the ſtricteſt ties of Juſtice and Gratitude Not to pay our juſt <note place="margin">Gratitude to Benefactors, the contrary too common.</note> Debts when we are able, is a Vice almoſt unpardonable, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> be ungrateful to a Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefactor, however common it may be in this unthankful Age, is an Act the moſt ſordidly baſe and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingenieus.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="part">
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:135637:52"/>
               <head>PARTITION XIV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of Duty to Magiſtrates, Paſtors. Of the Duty of Parents to Children, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Of Childrens Duty to Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>I Come now to the <note place="margin">Duty to Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents.</note> neareſt kind of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, and in the firſt Rank of thoſe I place our Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to Parents, whether Civil, Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual or Natural.</p>
               <p>The Civil Parent is <note place="margin">To the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour.</note> he who by a juſt right poſſeſſes the Throne, and to him we owe Honour and Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence; we are to look upon him, as a Perſon upon whom God has ſtamp'd a great deal of his own Power and Authority, and upon no Account to ſpeak evil of him or revile him.</p>
               <p>Next we owe him our Tribute, which we are to pay him with the
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:135637:53"/> utmoſt, both of Juſtice and Freedom; Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <note place="margin">Tribute, Prayers and Obedience.</note> We are to Pray for him, that God would direct and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt him in all his Undertakings. And Fourthly, We owe him a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn and ſtrict Obedience; which both the Laws of God and Nature have commanded us to obſerve wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the moſt awful and religious Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion.</p>
               <p>The ſecond ſorts of Parents a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the Spiritual, <hi>viz.</hi> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Miniſters of God<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <note place="margin">Duties to our Paſtors.</note> Word, and ſuch a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> are entruſted with the Salvation of Souls; to them we owe the higheſt Love and Kindneſs we are oblig'd to eſteem and value them as our beſt and trueſt Friends we are likewiſe to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute to their Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, <note place="margin">Love, Eſteem Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and Prayer.</note> and witha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to look upon them a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Gods Meſſengers, and upon that Account t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> behave our ſelves <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:135637:53"/> them with a great deal of diſtance and reſpect, and to put up our ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Prayers to God for them, that he would grant them the aſſiſtance of his Spirit, to enable them right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to diſcharge their Holy Calling.</p>
               <p>The third ſort of Parent is the Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, <note place="margin">Duties to our Natural Parent.</note> by which is meant the Fathers of our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>leſh. Towards theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e are to demean our <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Reverence, Love,</hi> &amp;c.</note> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>lves with Reverence and Humility, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pon no Account to contemn or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſpiſe them, either in our outward <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ehaviour or in our Hearts; we we them our moſt ardent Love and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ndereſt Affection, and ought to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>hor every thing that can give them the leaſt Cauſe of Grief or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſquiet.</p>
               <p>We owe likewiſe <note place="margin">Obedience.</note> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r Obedience to all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Commands of our Parents, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e not oppoſite to the Laws of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>od, and cannot violate them, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>thout expoſing our ſelves to the
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:135637:54"/> Puniſhments he has ſo often de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounc'd in Scripture againſt diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient Children.</p>
               <p>Children are not to Marry without the <note place="margin">Children not to Marry without the Conſent of their Parents</note> Conſent of their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, every Child is ſo much the Right and Poſſeſſion of his Parent, that he mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> be guilty of Theft to diſpoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> himſelf without his Conſent. We are likewiſe bound according to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Abilities, to ſupp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> their Wants, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <note place="margin">To provide for their Wants. Duties to the worſt of Parents.</note> adminiſter to them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> any kind of Extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: and all this is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> be done, even to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> worſt of Parents.</p>
               <p>But as there a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> many things due fro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <note place="margin">Duties of Parents to Children.</note> the Child to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, ſo there are ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> from the Parent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Child. The Parent is oblig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to nouriſh and ſuſtain the Chi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> till he comes of Age to do it
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:135637:54"/> himſelf, he is likewiſe to take Care for his Soul, by bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him early to the <note place="margin">To bring them to Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm; to edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate them.</note> Sacrament of Baptiſm; and by having him timely inſtructed in the Principles of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and educated in the true Faith, and Fear of God; and as a Means to improve his Education too; he is <note place="margin">Means to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards their Education.</note> to encourage and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect him, and to uſe all wiſe and gentle Means in order to impreſs upon him a timely Sence of Vertue, and good Morals.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, The Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent <note place="margin">The Parent to watch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Childs Soul.</note> is to watch over the Soul of his Child after he comes to years of Maturity, and as often as he finds occaſion, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort, encourage and reprove him; he is likewiſe to take Care of his outward <note place="margin">To provide for their Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtenance.</note> State, by providing him with a ſuitable
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:135637:55"/> Condition of Life; but above all, he is to lay before him a good Example, <note place="margin">To give them good Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</note> and to make his own Life a fit Pattern for him, from whence he may tranſcribe the true Rules of Vertue, Honour, Honeſty and God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs; and then he is to Bleſs him, and Pray <note place="margin">To Bleſs them, and to give them no unreaſonable Commands.</note> for him, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend him often to God's Care and Protection: And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, all this too, he muſt be extreamly careful, that all the Commands he laies upon him are juſt and reaſonable, and in all reſpects utterly diſtant from all ſorts of harſhneſs or ſeverity.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="part">
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:135637:55"/>
               <head>PARTITION XV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of Duties to our Brethren, and Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; Husband, Wife, Friends, Maſters, Servants.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THE ſecond ſort <note place="margin">Duties to Brethren: Natural Love.</note> of Relation is that of a Brother, which we may take in a double Sence, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Natural or Spiritual. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin with the Firſt, the Duties be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Natural Brethren, I mean ſuch that are of the ſame immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate Parents. And the Duty of theſe is to have united Hearts and Affections, to love one another with great Tenderneſs and Since<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and to do their utmoſt to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote their mutual Good and Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs; This is a Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſo neceſſary in all <note place="margin">The neceſſity of Love a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren.</note> Points, that without <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t no Family, where there is any number
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:135637:56"/> of Brothers, and Siſters, can pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe any tolerable Eaſe or Satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
               <p>The ſecond ſort are Spiritual Brethren, <note place="margin">Spiritual Brethren.</note> under which Notion are comprehended all thoſe that are baptiz'd in the ſame Faith, and Church with our ſelves, and to all theſe our Compaſſion is to be the moſt melting and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate; with theſe we are to profeſs and defend the Faith of Chriſt Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cify'd, and to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate with 'em in <note place="margin">Our Duty to hold Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with them. To bear their Infirmities, to reſtore them after falls, and to ſympathize with them.</note> all Holy Offices, we are to bear with their Infirmities, and in a friendly manner to admoniſh and reprove 'em, and by fair and gentle Methods to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to bring them to Repentance after they are fall'n. We are to ſympathize with them in all their Agonies and Diſtreſſes, whether of Soul, Mind, or Body.</p>
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:135637:56"/>
               <p>The third Relation is that between Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band <note place="margin">The Wife owes to the Husband O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity and Love.</note> and Wife, this is the neareſt Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all, and yet there are ſeveral re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Duties which they owe to each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for the Wife in the firſt Place, ſhe owes her Huſband Obedience, which God has ſtrictly commanded her to pay him in all things that are Juſt and Lawful; ſhe owes him Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity both to his Bed and his world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Affairs, ſhe owes him likewiſe her Love, and is bound to behave her ſelf to him with the greateſt friendlineſs and ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. And this ſhe is <note place="margin">The faults of the Husband acquit her not from theſe Duties.</note> to do notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his faults, which will by no means ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit her of any of theſe Duties.</p>
               <p>There are likewiſe <note place="margin">Duties from the Husband to the Wife: Love,</note> ſeveral Duties owing from the Huſband to the Wife; the Firſt,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:135637:57"/> Is Love, by which he is enjoin'd to treat her with the utmoſt Tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Compaſſion, not to behave himſelf to her with any manner of harſhneſs or ſeverity, but to uſe her in all reſpects as a part of himſelf.</p>
               <p>Secondly, He owes Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity to her Bed, this <note place="margin">Faithfulneſs to her Bed,</note> is as much the Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands Duty as the Wife's, and the breach of it in ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, is an Act of Uncleanneſs, and Perjury. Thirdly, He is bound to do his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour <note place="margin">To maintain and inſtruct her.</note> to provide for her, and to ſuffer her freely to partake of all his outward Bleſſings; and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the reſt of his Duties, he is chiefly to take Care of the Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of her Soul, and to inſtruct her as far as her need requires in the Principles of Honeſty and Religion.</p>
               <p>In brief, Huſbands and Wives are mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally <note place="margin">Husbands &amp; Wives bound to pray for, and aſſiſt each other.</note> bound to Pray for each other, and to their utmoſt to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagate
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:135637:57"/> their Reciprocal Good and Happineſs.</p>
               <p>The true Ends of <note place="margin">The true Ends of Marriage to be conſulted, and unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Marria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voided.</note> Marriage are likewiſe to be conſulted; in which Caſe the Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Mind are ſooner to be cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, then either Wealth, or Beauty, or any other outward Appendage; above all the reſt, unlawful Marriages are to be avoided, 'tis a Holy State and ſhould never be enter'd into, but according to the Direction of the Church, Reverently, Adviſedly, Soberly, and in the Fear of God.</p>
               <p>The next thing is Friendſhip, which is <note place="margin">Friendſhip with its Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</note> of that common good and concern, that hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Life would be but a wretched thing <note place="margin">Faithfulneſs, Aſſiſtance, Admonition, Prayer, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy.</note> without it; the Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of it are many, but the moſt material are Faithfulneſs in our
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:135637:58"/> Truſts; Aſſiſtance, either with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to our Souls, or Bodies; to our Souls, eſpecially in admoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us of our faults; which is the higheſt and moſt exalted Act of Friendſhip that can paſs between Man and Man. Prayer is the next Duty, and after that Conſtancy, and all theſe together render a Friend an ineſtimable Jewel.</p>
               <p>The Laſt Relation is that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Maſters, and Servants, and theſe too are mutually engag'd to each other. The Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant is bound to obey <note place="margin">Servants owe to their Maſters, Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, Fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, Submiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, Dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence.</note> his Maſter's juſt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, and to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute them with Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Satisfaction; he owes him likewiſe an univerſal Fidelity in all his Concerns; and is oblig'd by all the Rules of Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, and good Manners, to bear his Rebukes, and Reprehenſions, with Submiſſion, and to diſcharge his Truſt, in every Particular, with Diligence, and Application.</p>
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:135637:58"/>
               <p>The Maſters on the other ſide, owe to <note place="margin">Maſters owe to their Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants: Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition, Means of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, Moderation in Command, Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> their Servants Juſtice, in providing them with convenient Food, and paying them their Wages; as alſo Admonitions and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofs, with regard as well to their Sins and Offences againſt God, as Faults againſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. They owe 'em likewiſe good Example, that is, they are to make their own Lives and Actions a fit Preſident for them to walk by; they are to allow them opportunities for Inſtruction, and convenient time for the Publick Worſhip of God; moreover they are to command them with Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and Moderation; to encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage their well doing, and to treat their Faithfulneſs, Diligence, and Piety with a great deal of Kindneſs and Bounty.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="part">
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:135637:59"/>
               <head>PARTITION XVI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Other Branches of our Duty to our Neighbour. Of Charity to Men's Souls, Bodies, Goods and Credit.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THE next Duty <note place="margin">Charity in the Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> to our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour is Charity, this is a Duty which the Bleſſed JESUS himſelf has ſolemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enjoyn'd in his Holy Goſpel, and may be conſidered two Ways, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in our Affections, or Actions; and Firſt, The Charity of Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, is ſuch an univerſal Kindneſs, that inclines us to wiſh well to the Soul, Body, Goods, and Credit, of all Mankind.</p>
               <p>To their Souls in the firſt Place, and to <note place="margin">To Men's Souls, Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, Goods, and Credit.</note> them we cannot ſure but wiſh well, when we conſider, that Chriſt thought their Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome worth the Price of his own
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:135637:59"/> Blood; we owe next all the good we can to the Bodies of Men; this is an high Article of our Charity, and without it, we can never come up to that golden Rule, of loving our Neighbour as our ſelves. His Goods, and his Credit, are like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to be very dear, and precious to us, and we are bound to propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate his Intereſt, and Reputation, and to eſteem them upon all Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts equal to our own.</p>
               <p>This kind of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity naturally begets <note place="margin">The Effects of this Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</note> in us a quiet and peaceable Mind, and a Compaſſion and Tenderneſs towards others; it cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ates in us a Joy for their Proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and excites us to Pray for 'em, and to importune Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God in their <note place="margin">It caſts out Envy, Pride, Cenſoriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling, Self<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>love and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge.</note> behalf; beſides all theſe too, it guards our Minds againſt all ſort of Envy or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, keeps down our Pride, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſes
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:135637:60"/> deep upon us the Grace of Humility; it deſtroys Cenſoriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and curbs the raſhneſs of our Judgment, ſuppreſſes Diſſimulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and baniſhes, and ſubverts, all feign'd, and pretended Kindneſs; it caſts away all Self-love, and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenary Deſigns, and intirely roots out of our Minds all manner of Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor and Malice.</p>
               <p>Nay, this Charity goes further, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <note place="margin">The Motives to it, Chriſt's Commands, and the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of God</note> to the Doctrine and Example of our Bleſſed Lord, it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends it ſelf even to our Enemies; and what can be a greater Motive to it, then to find it ſo ſolemnly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded and enforc'd by God's own Preſident.</p>
               <p>This is a Subject well becoming our <note place="margin">This Charity to extend e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</note> ſerious Conſideration, and ſhould put us in mind methinks, to ballance our Sins a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God, with the Offences of our
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:135637:60"/> Brethren againſt our ſelves, and would we do that, we ſhould find the firſt ſo much outweigh the laſt, that from a fair Compariſon, we muſt needs judge our ſelves very unworthy to expect God ſhould Pardon us <note place="margin">The Diſpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of our Offences againſt God compar'd with Men's againſt us.</note> for ſo many great of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, and yet at the ſame time we refuſe to forgive our Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren for ſome, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, trivial faults; beſides this too, there's a great deal of Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure <note place="margin">Pleaſantneſs of this Duty.</note> and Satisfaction in the forgiving our Enemies; 'tis true, this may ſeem a Paradox at firſt ſight, but then, if we examine the Truth of it by Experience, we ſhall find it really ſo, and this ſort of forgiving Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, the moſt delightful as well as the moſt Chriſtian.</p>
               <p>Beyond this likewiſe, there is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Conſideration ſtrong enough to engage us to forgive our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, I mean the danger of it; God
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:135637:61"/> has made our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion to others, the <note place="margin">If we forgive not, God will not forgive us.</note> Standard by which he intends to meaſure his to us. If ye for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give not Men their Treſpaſſes, neither will your Father forgive your Treſpaſſes, nay, he has made it a part of our daily Prayers, ſo that when a revengeful Perſon ſays this Prayer, he lays up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on himſelf a Curſe, and does in ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect beg God not to forgive him.</p>
               <p>This is a Duty we are oblig'd to in Point of Gratitude too; God has ſhew'd <note place="margin">Gratitude to God.</note> us wonderful Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, and can we be ſo baſe to think, we are not oblig'd to ſome returns. Peace and Unity was one of the laſt things our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour recommended to the World, and indeed he has preſs'd no ſingle Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept <note place="margin">The firſt ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor to be ſuppreſt.</note> with greater con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern than this of uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Charity and forgiving Enemies, a
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:135637:61"/> Conſideration methinks, that ſhould engage us to ſuppreſs all Degrees of Ranchor and Revenge, and to check and curb them in their very firſt Motions.</p>
               <p>I come now to the <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Charity in the Actions, to the Mind, Soul, Body,</hi> &amp;c.</note> Charity in the Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which is the tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt way to prove the former, I mean by a ſincere and cordial Love, diſtributed without Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie, or Reſerve, to the Soul, Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, Goods, and Credit of our Neighbour; to his Soul and Mind, we ſhould acquit our ſelves with the utmoſt tenderneſs and concern, and omit no means that might any ways promote the Happineſs or Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of either; to his Body we ſhould exerciſe all the Offices of true Chriſtian Friendſhip and Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and upon all occaſions be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly ready to promote his Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, and defend his Reputation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="part">
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:135637:62"/>
               <head>PARTITION XVII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of Charity; Alms-giving, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Of Charity in reſpect of our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours Credit, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Of Peace ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, of going to Law, of Charity to our Enemies.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THE next thing <note place="margin">Charity in reſpect of the Goods, both to the Rich and Poor.</note> is our Charity, towards the Goods and Eſtate of our Neighbour, and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we are to aſſiſt and further him in all honeſt and friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Offices, and this we are to do to the Rich as well as the Poor on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with this difference, that the Poor are the more immediate Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of our Alms.</p>
               <p>This great Duty of Alms-giving is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forc'd <note place="margin">Motives of Alms-giving</note> by many ſtrong and powerful Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, but the three greateſt of all are with reſpect to God, our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:135637:62"/> and our Selves, God has commanded it, and expects it both as an Argument of our Obedience and Thankfulneſs. Secondly, True Love and Compaſſion, and a Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-feeling of our Neighbours Wants and Sufferings engage us to it. Thirdly, In reſpect of our Selves, the Motive is, that there is an Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Reward annext; the manner is likewiſe <note place="margin">Manner of Alms-giving</note> to be carefully con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted, which will add much to the Grace it ſelf, and to the Advantage of thoſe we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve.</p>
               <p>And Firſt, We are <note place="margin">Chearfully without the Apprehenſion of Want, ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably, pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently, and liberally.</note> to do it always with the greateſt chearful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and ſatisfaction to exerciſe a kind of Holy Joy in dealing our Bread to the hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry; we muſt not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain any vain Fears, or impious Apprehenſions, that our admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring to the Wants of the Diſtreſt will be any means to Impoveriſh us
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:135637:63"/> or conſume our Eſtates. We are likewiſe to obſerve a due ſeaſon and order of Time, and a Prudent and Religious Care in the regular Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribution of our Charity, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al to do it purſuant to the Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Liberality and true Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Generoſity.</p>
               <p>Our Charity like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe obliges us to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve <note place="margin">Charity in reſpect of our Neighbours Credit.</note> and propagate the Credit of our Neighbour, to be our ſelves very tender and careful of his Reputation, and to defend and promote it among o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, with all the Caution that we are able; to be unwilling to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve his Faults, and to conceal them as far as 'tis lawful from the Publick, and to uſe all friendly means to adviſe and reclaim him.</p>
               <p>This is the ſumm of that Active Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty <note place="margin">Acts of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity in ſome reſpects, Acts of Juſtice.</note> we owe to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Capacities of our Brethren, and this indeed according
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:135637:63"/> to the true meaning of it, is a kind of Juſtice we owe to him. Likewiſe Juſtice and Charity are ſo near al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly'd, that they are not to be ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated, the one conſtantly depends upon the other, and they can never be devided without Injury to both.</p>
               <p>To improve this excellent Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, we can do nothing better, then by laying <note place="margin">The great Rule of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</note> always before us that great Rule of Loving our Neighbour as our Selves, this the Apoſtle makes the ſumm of our Duty; and indeed we can hardly erre if we make that the Standard whereby to meaſure our Actions.</p>
               <p>Peace-making is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother <note place="margin">Peace-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king.</note> Act of Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and may be of great uſe both to his Soul, Body, Goods, and Credit. God himſelf has pronounc'd the Peace-maker bleſs'd, an encouragements ſufficient to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage us to lay hold on all opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities of ſetting upon this extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Work of Charity; but firſt
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:135637:64"/> every Man ought to have a ſpecial regard to his own Temper; he that will undertake in ſuch an excellent Office, <note place="margin">He that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakes it, muſt be peaceable himſelf.</note> has need to be qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified with all th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Graces of Peace, Meekneſs, and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</p>
               <p>Contentions, and Quarrels, and Litigious Suits and Controverſies ought to be appeas'd and taken up with all the Caution that can be.</p>
               <p>The going to Law i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Cauſe be Juſt has <note place="margin">Of going to Law.</note> commonly ſo many unhappy Appendages, that according to the Judgment of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> the tender regard we ought to have for Peace, ſhould ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther encline us to take Wrong and ſuffer our ſelves to be defraud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed then make uſe of it.</p>
               <p>All that remains now, is the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of this Charity; which is to reach to all Order<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and Degrees of Men even <note place="margin">Charity to Enemies.</note> to our very Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies;
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:135637:64"/> this was our Bleſſed Lord's own Example, then which, there can be nothing greater to recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend it to us.</p>
               <p>And thus I have run through the ſeveral Parts of our Duty to our Neighbour, towards the right Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of which there is nothing certainly can more conduce then the root<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <note place="margin">Self-love an hinderance to this Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</note> out of our Hearts all kind of inor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate Love of our ſelves; this is an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy Principle indeed, and where it once takes root it ſoon choaks both our Charity and our Juſtice; if therefore, we ever intend our Charity ſhould grow in our Minds, we muſt firſt weed out of 'em this Sin of Self-love, for 'tis impoſſible they can proſper together, and then, when this and all other hinderances are remov'd, we are to fly to our grand Remedy, Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, that God would <note place="margin">Prayer a means to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure it.</note> frame our Hearts in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſuch a galleſs Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:135637:65"/> that we may be enabled right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to perform this great Duty.</p>
               <p>And now I have done with thoſe ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral <note place="margin">Chriſtian Duties, both poſſible and pleaſant.</note> things I at firſt propos'd, in ſhewing what is our Duty to God, our Selves, and our Neighbour; and ſurely, through the whole, there ſeems nothing of Impoſſibility; the things themſelves are all reaſonable Juſt and Practica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and what's more delightful and pleaſant too; even thoſe that may ſeem to expoſe us to Perſecutions and <note place="margin">Even when they expoſe us to Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</note> Suffering from their Ends and Conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are the Objects of more Joy then Grief. There is ſuch a Power in Vertue, ſuch a Satisfaction in a good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and ſuch a Secret and conſtant Pleaſure in the Perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of the Chriſtian Duties, that there is no Apology to be made for our Neglect; beſide, 'tis a dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous thing to defer our return to
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:135637:65"/> God, the Particulars I have ſet down in <note place="margin">The danger of delaying our turning to God.</note> the Diſcourſe of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and thither I refer you; with the Wiſe Kings moſt ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Advice, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 5. 7. <hi>Make no tarrying to turn to the Lord, and put not off from Day to Day.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayers">
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>An Introductory Prayer for Faith.</head>
                  <p>BLeſſed Lord, God, ſtrengthen and confirm my Faith I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee thee, that I may truly believe and depend upon thy Holy Name, and Word; improve my Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, and direct my Will, that whatſoever I read in this, or any Book tending to the Promotion of Religion, and the Salvation of my Soul, may ſink ſo deep into my Mind, that I may bring forth by it, the Fruit of good Living, to thy Praiſe and Honour: O Jeſus, my only Mediator and Advocate.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <pb n="122" facs="tcp:135637:66"/>
                  <head>A Prayer ſuited for the Firſt Partition.</head>
                  <p>INſtruct me O my God, in the <hi>Whole Duty of Man;</hi> enrich me with thy <hi>bleſſed Spirit,</hi> that the <hi>Lights</hi> of <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Scripture</hi> may ſhine bright in me, and guide me, through the diſtinct <hi>Branches</hi> of my <hi>Duty,</hi> to <hi>Thee,</hi> my <hi>Self,</hi> and my <hi>Neighbour.</hi> Give me O <hi>Jeſus,</hi> mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful <hi>Jeſus,</hi> ſuch an awful Sence of thy <hi>Eternal Eſſence,</hi> that by a ſtea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and unalterable <hi>Faith</hi> I may lay hold on thy gracious <hi>Promiſes;</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove and enliven my <hi>hope</hi> by a fixt and ſolid Dependance upon thy <hi>Goodneſs,</hi> and yet reſtrain me too, that I may in no reſpect be poſſeſt with the Vanity of Preſumption. O <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Love,</hi> inſpire my Soul with ſuch a Holy Ardency, that I may make it the whole buſineſs of my Life to Adore and Love Thee. O <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Love!</hi> Let the <hi>Fear</hi> of Thee (O glorious Majeſty!) poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes me with ſuch a Holy Reverence, and Regard for Thee, that I may
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:135637:66"/> be afraid to do any thing againſt the Honour due to thy <hi>Name,</hi> or to provoke Thee with any kind of Sin, or Folly; and in all my Wants and Extremities, give me Grace to put my whole <hi>Truſt</hi> and Confidence in Thee: O Almighty Lord!</p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>For the Second.</head>
                  <p>ENdow me, <hi>O Lamb</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> with a Spirit of <hi>Meekneſs</hi> and <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility,</hi> that I may be enabl'd to <hi>ſubmit</hi> to thy <hi>Will,</hi> and to undergo all the <hi>Sufferings</hi> of my Life with Calmneſs and Moderation. O thou Eternal <hi>Fountain</hi> of all <hi>Honour, Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> and <hi>Power,</hi> for thy <hi>own</hi> ſake I beſeech Thee impreſs deeply upon my Soul, a high <hi>Reverence</hi> and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard</hi> for thy <hi>Houſe</hi> the <hi>Church,</hi> and the <hi>Poſſeſſions</hi> thou haſt ſet a part for thy own Uſe, and let thy <hi>Day,</hi> thy <hi>Word,</hi> and thy <hi>Sacraments</hi> be always precious in my ſight; O Lord! my <hi>Strength,</hi> and my <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <pb n="124" facs="tcp:135637:67"/>
                  <head>For the Third.</head>
                  <p>O Merciful Jeſus, who haſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par'd a bleſſed <hi>Feaſt</hi> for the Entertainmment of my Soul, give me Grace before I preſume to approach thy <hi>Table</hi> to prove my Self by a ſtrict <hi>Examination,</hi> how fit I am to be a <hi>Gueſt</hi> at ſuch an Holy <hi>Banquet;</hi> and ſeeing I can never prepare my ſelf as I ought without <hi>Repentance, Faith,</hi> and <hi>Obedience:</hi> Direct me I beſeech Thee, in the right performance of thoſe great <hi>Duties,</hi> and in every other Grace and Vertue that is any ways requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to qualifie me aright for that awful <hi>Myſtery.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>For the Fourth.</head>
                  <p>O <hi>Omnipotent</hi> and <hi>Eternal God,</hi> I acknowledg'd thy <hi>Name</hi> is <hi>Great, Wonderful,</hi> and <hi>Holy,</hi> and moſt worthy of <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> keep me therefore (dread <hi>Lord)</hi> from all kind of <hi>Blaſphemy,</hi>
                     <pb n="125" facs="tcp:135637:67"/> and <hi>Perjury,</hi> and from all <hi>vain</hi> and <hi>unlawful Oaths,</hi> and from every o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Sin that may any ways tend to debaſe the <hi>Majeſty</hi> of thy moſt glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious <hi>Name.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>For the Fifth.</head>
                  <p>THY Name O <hi>Lord</hi> is thy own glorious <hi>Self!</hi> Hear me there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore O great Jehova! That when I Pray, Repent, or Faſt, or do any of the other Duties of Religion, I may do them all with an habitual Reverence, and Purity of Intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to the Praiſe and Honour of thy Name.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>For the Sixth.</head>
                  <p>DIrect me O my <hi>God</hi> in the <hi>Duties</hi> to my <hi>Self!</hi> Impreſs upon me O <hi>Eternal Goodneſs,</hi> a <hi>ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber Mind,</hi> and an <hi>Humble</hi> Spirit, that I may acquit my ſelf to Thee and my Fellow-Creature, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes a Wiſe Man and a good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian; keep I beſeech Thee all <hi>Pride</hi>
                     <pb n="126" facs="tcp:135637:68"/> and <hi>Vain-Glory</hi> out of my Heart, and from a due Reflection upon the <hi>Folly</hi> and <hi>Danger</hi> that attends them, give me Grace to uſe the means to prevent 'em effectually; endow me O thou Author of all good Gifts, with a <hi>meek</hi> and quiet Spirit, that I may form my Life af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thy Example; O bleſſed Jeſus!</p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>For the Seventh.</head>
                  <p>BLeſs me O Father of Mercy with a <hi>contented</hi> Mind through every State and Turn of my Life, and let neither <hi>Murmuring,</hi> Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Covetouſneſs, or Envy at any time get the Dominion over my Reaſon, and diſturb the Compoſure of my Soul. Aſſiſt me mercifully O Lord in the performance of thoſe Duties that concern my Body, that by the help of <hi>Chaſtity</hi> and <hi>Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,</hi> I may utterly mortifie all my Corrupt Luſts and Appetites, and make it a fit Receptacle for a pure Mind, and a quiet Conſcience.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <pb n="127" facs="tcp:135637:68"/>
                  <head>For the Eighth.</head>
                  <p>GIve me, O thou Eternal Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of all Order and Sobrie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, a fixt and ſetl'd Hatred againſt all <hi>Intemperance,</hi> but more eſpecially againſt that of exceſſive Drinking; diſcover to me I beſeech Thee, the falſe Ends of Drinking, and imprint upon me ſuch a deep ſence of the Danger, and Folly, and withal of the Loathſomeneſs of it, that I may reject it, as a Vice much below the Dignity of a Man, much more of a Chriſtian.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>For the Ninth.</head>
                  <p>O Holy, Holy, Holy, Lord, God, direct me I beſeech Thee in a right Application of all thy Bleſſings. Thou haſt given me leave to <hi>Sleep</hi> for the Support and Repoſe of my Frail Body, teach me likewiſe, O God of Temperance, to meaſure it by the Ends for which thou was at firſt pleas'd to ordain
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:135637:69"/> it. Let all my <hi>Recreations</hi> be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate and inoffenſive, and us'd with the ſtricteſt <hi>Caution</hi> with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to <hi>Thee,</hi> my <hi>Neighbour,</hi> and my <hi>Self;</hi> give me Grace and Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to avoid all Gaiety in my Apparel, and to prefer the inward Ornaments of my Soul to all uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Trappins, and all gaudy and inſignificant Shews and Formalities.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>For the Tenth.</head>
                  <p>INſtruct me, O Eternal Father of all Truth and Equity, in the <hi>Duties</hi> I owe to my <hi>Neighbour;</hi> grant I beſeech Thee, that I may direct my Life, by the conſtant Rules of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> both <hi>Negative</hi> and <hi>Poſitive.</hi> Prevent me, O Crucify'd Saviour from that crying Sin of Murder; let the <hi>hainouſneſs,</hi> the <hi>Puniſhments,</hi> and the <hi>ſtrange Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries</hi> thou haſt been pleas'd to make of it be always in my View, to deter me from it even in the moſt minute Particulars.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <pb n="129" facs="tcp:135637:69"/>
                  <head>For the Eleventh.</head>
                  <p>GIve me Grace, O Bleſſed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer that after thy Example I may obſerve a ſtrict and <hi>Poſitive Juſtice to my Neighbour</hi> in all his <hi>Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions.</hi> Stamp deep upon my Mind I intreat Thee (O my God) a tender regard for him in his <hi>Wife,</hi> and in all his worldly <hi>Goods.</hi> Lord I beſeech Thee, defend me from the Sins of <hi>Oppreſſion</hi> and <hi>Theft,</hi> and give me Grace to acquit my Self juſtly in all my Dealings, and to behave my ſelf as becomes an honeſt Man in all manner of <hi>Bargains and Commerce.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>For the Twelfth.</head>
                  <p>LET thy merciful Ears O Lord be open to my Prayers; for the ſake of thy own Eternal Equity, errace utterly out of my Mind all unjuſt Notions; and let no Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations to any ſort of <hi>Robbery</hi> at any time get the Dominion over me;
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:135637:70"/> improve my Mind I beſeech Thee with ſuch a determinate hatred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all kind of <hi>Deceit,</hi> that I may immediately reſolve upon that great Duty of a Chriſtian Reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And this I beg of Thee with the higheſt Ardency, for thy own ſake O merciful Jeſus!</p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>For the Thirteenth.</head>
                  <p>O Eternal God of Truth! guide me I beſeech Thee by thy bleſſed Spirit, that I may be exactly careful how I <hi>Believe,</hi> or <hi>Report</hi> any thing to the Prejudice of my Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour; keep me from the dangerous Sins of <hi>Perjury.</hi> and <hi>Slandering,</hi> from all baſe and malicious <hi>Whiſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings,</hi> and from all fly and injurious Inſinuations; O God of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, let the tenderneſs and regard I owe to my Fellow Chriſtian ſink ſo deep into my Soul, that I may neither Scoff at his <hi>Calamities,</hi> or <hi>Infirmities,</hi> nor <hi>deride</hi> his very <hi>Sins.</hi> Give me, O King of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> ſuch a <hi>Poſitive <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>prightneſs</hi> and <hi>Integrity,</hi>
                     <pb n="131" facs="tcp:135637:70"/> that I may abhor all ſorts of <hi>Lying, Envy,</hi> and <hi>Detraction,</hi> and that I may preſerve an humble and intire <hi>Gratitude</hi> and Thankfulneſs towards my Friends and Benefactors, but eſpecially towards Thee O bounti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Jeſus!</p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>For the Fourteenth.</head>
                  <p>O God of all Order and Power, who in thy Wiſdom haſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed ſeveral Ranks and Degrees of Men among us, give me an awful Sence of that profound <hi>Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience</hi> and Reſpect I owe to all the <hi>Magiſtrates, Paſtors,</hi> and <hi>Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours</hi> in their reſpective Stations; teach me O my God! as a <hi>Child,</hi> that <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Reverence</hi> I owe to my <hi>Parents,</hi> and as a <hi>Parent</hi> that <hi>Care</hi> and <hi>Duty</hi> I owe to my <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,</hi> that in both Capacities I may diſcharge my Truſt after the Direction of thy moſt Holy Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts, O King of Righteouſneſs!</p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <pb n="132" facs="tcp:135637:71"/>
                  <head>For the Fifteenth.</head>
                  <p>TEach me O merciful God and Saviour, that I may acquit my ſelf to all my <hi>Brethren</hi> whether <hi>Spiritual</hi> or <hi>Temporal,</hi> and to all my <hi>Relations,</hi> as becomes a Member of the Chriſtian Profeſſion; in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Capacities of a <hi>Husband, Friend, Maſter</hi> and <hi>Servant,</hi> teach me O merciful God, to behave my ſelf, as becomes a Member of thy moſt Holy Religion, O bleſſed Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>For the Sixteenth.</head>
                  <p>INſtruct me I beſeech Thee, O <hi>Almighty Lord,</hi> in all the <hi>Branches</hi> of my <hi>Duty</hi> to my Neighbour. After thy own Example, O un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable Goodneſs! Direct my Charity towards him, with reſpect to his <hi>Soul,</hi> his <hi>Body,</hi> his <hi>Goods,</hi> and his <hi>Credit;</hi> give me ſuch a Spirit of Poſitive Juſtice, that I may value him upon all Accounts equal to my
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:135637:71"/> ſelf, and be always ready to do the very beſt I can to propagate his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in both Worlds. I beg this of Thee with the utmoſt Ardency of my Soul, O Jeſus, merciful Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus!</p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>For the Seventeenth.</head>
                  <p>O Merciful God, who haſt mark'd out my <hi>Compaſſion</hi> to my Fellow Creature, as the Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard by which thou intendeſt to meaſure Thine to me! Give me, I beſeech Thee an intire and univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal <hi>Charity.</hi> Open my Bowels, that I may be ready to help and further him in all his <hi>Extremities.</hi> Grant O my God, for the ſake of thy own Love, that I may be always prepar'd to vindicate my Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours good Name upon all occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that I may judge the beſt and ſpeak well of him, and conceal or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe his Infirmities, that I may be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patient to hear, ſlow to believe and unwilling to propagate evil <hi>Reports;</hi> lodge him in my Heart in the very
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:135637:72"/> next Place to my Self, that I may conſtantly Study his <hi>Peace,</hi> and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue it equal to my own; keep me from all <hi>Litigious Suits</hi> and <hi>Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies,</hi> let an even and regular <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> run through my whole Life and Actions, and extend it ſelf even to my very <hi>Enemies;</hi> I beg this and every thing elſe, thou in thy Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom knows uſeful for me, for Jeſus Chriſt his Sake,</p>
                  <trailer>Amen, Amen.</trailer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:135637:72"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Books Printed for</hi> John Lawrence <hi>at the</hi> Angel <hi>in the</hi> Poultrey.</head>
            <p>CAtholiciſm without Popery. An Eſſay to render the Church of <hi>England</hi> a Means and a Pattern of Union to the Chriſtian World. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ctavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Mourners Companion: Or, Funeral Diſcourſes on ſeveral Texts, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n Two Parts. By Mr. <hi>John Show<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Dying Mans Aſſiſtant: Or, Short Inſtructions for thoſe who are concerned in the preparing of Sick Perſons for Death. Being no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſs worthy the Conſideration of all good Chriſtians in time of Health; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hewing the importance of an Early Preparation for their latter End;
<pb facs="tcp:135637:73"/> with regard as well to their Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral, as Eternal State. By a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine of the Church of <hi>England Twelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>London</hi> Diſpenſatory, redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to the Practiſe of the <hi>London</hi> Phyſicians, wherein are contained the Medicines that are now in uſe, and ſuch as are not in the Latine Copy added; with their Vertues and Uſe. By <hi>John Pechy</hi> of the Colledge of Phyſicians in <hi>London, Twelves.</hi> Price 1 <hi>s. 6 d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Clark</hi>'s Concordance to the Bible. <hi>Twelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:135637:73"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
